He will be a staff for the righteous, with which for them to stand and not to fall,
and he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits,
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits,
Angels, demons and saints in our time
many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see and to know reality
as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate
everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and Father Stephen De Young host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, all you gigantomocks out there.
You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host, Father Stephen D'Young, is with me
from Lafayette Louisiana,
and I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick in Emmaus, Pennsylvania.
This is not a live episode,
despite the entreaties from the voice of Steve
that you will hear to call in.
And this episode is pre-recorded for two reasons.
The first is that we're both going to be in church service.
tonight for the great feast of the Annunciation.
And the second is that our mothership studio in Chesterton, Indiana,
recently was flooded because of a water main break.
So Matyska Trudy and the rest of the local crew are in the process of getting the studio put
back together after a thorough cleaning and getting some new upgraded equipment installed as well.
And that means that ancient faith radio live shows can't take life calls right now.
And it's also why there was not an episode of Lord of Spirits to
weeks ago. You really got carried away with that house blessing. Yeah, too much, too much water
means that's the way of the future for house blessings. Just got to turn those things on. So anyway,
I was not anywhere near that now. But this episode, that's my official story. So, but this
episode is going to be a Q&A even though we can't take live calls actually because this time,
We're using
pre-recorded calls from you are listeners. Tonight we've got questions from all over the world
with topics ranging from catechism to giants to the Z's. The Z's. So are you ready, Father
Stephen? I am. Although I want to suggest that next time we have to do this, we actually post
record it. I don't know what that means but okay. That would be like the show airs on Thursday night and
and we recorded on Saturday morning.
That is to prove once and for all the whole time and space.
Time and space don't exist, yeah.
Okay.
Sounds good.
You'll always give it a shot.
I think.
We will see what we can do.
There's new equipment coming to the mothership,
so maybe it's got that capability.
All right, so here is our first question.
We're just gonna dive right on.
This one is from Christopher.
Corbynidges
Christfather's, my name is Christopher Mejale from Dambury, Connecticut.
And I know you've on multiple occasions said that liturgy does not mean the work of the people.
Would a better way of understanding it be work for the people as in God is doing the work for us.
Thanks again.
Have a good night.
Okay, so that's question.
Number one, and that is something we've talked about before.
So number one, shout out to Father Lucas Christensen,
who mentions this all the time.
And Richard Barrett, hello guys.
I don't know if you're listening.
But yeah, the reason that people think that liturgy
from Greek liturgya means work of the people
is because they see the words for people
and work in there, right?
And so that's then used to make this,
You know, okay, point about...
You should be participating in the divine liturgy and not seeing yourself merely as some kind of spectator, right?
So there's there is an actual basis for this comment, but it doesn't work in terms of actual historical usage. Is that right, Father?
Right. Yeah, that's sort of like, you know, butterfly, right? You don't take the two words and
Read them separately and then come to a conclusion or you'll be wrong. Yeah, so so how is the word used, you know, and
the context in which it actually arises.
Right, so originally, and by originally, I mean,
pre-Christian, pre-Greek translation
of the Old Testament, Greek, it basically means public works.
And it means public works in the sense of,
in the police, right?
You have...
of the city everyone.
Yes.
Although they are related, like many of police.
Minnesota.
Right.
Indiana police.
Yeah.
Exactly.
So you have to work on your modern Greek accent a little bit there.
Father.
I know it's not good.
I just offended a lot of people.
At least I didn't do the old Saturday at life.
Do you like the juice?
The juice.
It's good.
So, within the city, right, there would be at certain times public festivals, choruses
for theatrical performances, other kinds of public works that were of interest to city
life and the people, the citizens, the people who it Athens.
had the vote, but people who were at the citizen level, which wasn't everybody. But they were
expected to pay for those things. And that was part of your responsibility to the community.
Right. And the community, remember in the ancient world, including in ancient Greece, included
the gods. So the first person to use a phrase something like the divine liturgy.
is actually Aristotle. And when he uses that phrase, he's talking about the fact that a certain
amount of land should be given over by landowners to build temples. And so you can see how that's
both a religious activity, but also just sort of a public works project. Right.
So this then gets used to trans
a certain Hebrew verbs related specifically to the service of the Levites.
Okay.
And the reason it seems to get chosen, because there are other words, just for service or
religious devotion to this kind of thing, right?
The reason this particular word gets used in, first when the Torah is translated into Greek,
is that...
it's within the context of the covenant.
Right, so the covenant, remember, is, you know,
Yahweh the God of Israel is the king.
He cuts the covenant with the people,
identifies himself, lays out their responsibilities, right?
Just grabs the consequences.
And so, Lidia is a good word to use.
If that's your understanding of the services
outline of the Torah, right? The sacrificial...
system and this kind of thing.
This is your responsibility within the covenant toward God.
It's sort of this public work of the community aimed toward God.
Then it gets picked up that way in early Christianity because early Christianity saw themselves as
a people, not as a religion, remember, as something separate.
This was their identity as a people.
So their public work.
was Christian worship,
public referring to A people,
not to just people in general,
but A united right community.
And then this transition said very easily
once you get to say Constantine
because they already had this idea
of public works related to the pagan gods.
Yeah.
The Christian liturgy then replaces that,
beginning with the military under
and this gets translated in a couple of different ways into Latin.
One of them is Ministerium, which is where we get to our ministry.
And this is why, for example, in Great Britain, the departments of government are called ministries.
Right.
It's not because there's anything particularly religious about them.
It's this older concept of public service, public works.
United Kingdom.
is not a theocracy? Not for a long time. Right. And then the other one of those is
Ophysium, right, which is why you'll see, in a lot of English sources, you'll see various
services referred to as an office, whereas offices. The divine office. Right. And that's the word
the word of isyom essentially means something.
sort of similar to our concept of duty. Although our modern concept of duty has a
whole bunch of layers that Kant really be easily seen through by us. So it's duty in the sense of
responsibility. And so that's why office also gets used.
for, for example, what we call holy orders or the clergy,
they have an office that's a set of duties,
responsibilities, right?
Yeah, things you're supposed to do.
Yeah, but that's where Lidriae, literally,
that's where it comes from, that's what it means.
Yeah, so here's my follow up question,
because at the beginning of the divine liturgy,
if there is a deconserving, which ideally
There.
Oh, are we going to argue about this now?
No, no, I'm just asking about it.
Okay.
Because there's that line, there's that line which is translated variously as, because
this is sometimes brought up when people say, liturgy means, you know, work for the people
or public work or work by God, right?
There's that line that the deconsist, the priest, which is translated either as, it is time
to begin the service to the Lord, or sometimes it is time for the Lord to act.
And that's a translation from something in the Greek Old Testament, isn't it?
I'm trying to, I can't say anything.
Yeah.
So now is the time for the Lord to act sound much cooler, but is wrong.
Okay.
So the time to begin the service of the Lord is better.
That's accurate.
And I mean technically the Greek could go either way to translate the Greek.
Greek as now is the time for the Lord to act.
You have to do a little bit of special pleading
in terms of really uncommon Greek usages.
Yeah.
But if you look at the way that's translated
into all of the other languages in which Orthodox
liturgy is done, it's always something like
it's time to begin the service of the Lord.
Yeah, and I mean, because this raises the question of,
who is doing the divine liturgy, right?
And I
I think one of the problems is that there's on the one hand, you can shove it all to the
way to the one side and say, this is simply God doing it and we're here to show up and
receive it.
And then shove it all the way to the other side of it, like this is something we're doing
for or toward God.
And my understanding based on the prayers that are actually within it is that it is clearly
both, right?
that we are serving the Lord, but he is also doing something to and for us.
in the midst of it, that it's really, really is both.
Do you think that that's a good way to read it?
Yeah, I mean, we can get super technical with Greek and Latin here, which no one wants.
But, come on, someone wants it.
If you really dig into the usage of those both Greek and Latin words,
essentially the way a word like, you know, often
this or ministry works is it's essentially used instrumentally.
Right. I'm not going to go into all the Cicero and stuff we'd have to go into to demonstrate all this but
basically an analogy I'm pulling from Inkshire Usage is that the person who
conducts an office who conducts this duty or this responsibility or this role.
It's sort of like an axe.
Right? So you could say this axe chopped down the tree.
Okay. That's technically correct. Right? But the axe was instrumental. It was not the
actual agent of chopping down the tree. It is that through which the tree was chopped
down technically. But it had to fulfill its role in order for the chopping down of the
tree to happen. Gotcha.
So the idea then, if we apply those words sort of in their
original literal usage to the divine liturgy is that God is doing something and he's doing it instrumentally
through the clergy and the people.
Gotcha.
Well, that makes sense.
All right.
So, this is the first now of several questions we have from people named Ben or Benjamin.
I don't know why there's like five or six of them in this collection for this episode,
but here you are.
So, this has been number one.
Are any of them a rodent?
I am not certain none of them identified whether they were rodent.
or hominid or so I don't know that's up in the year.
So here's Ben.
Hi, fathers.
This is Ben calling from Grand Rapids, Michigan.
So I am currently an orthodox Christian
enrolled in a master's program within the mental health field.
And I had a professor in a recent lecture make
what I kind of thought was a bold statement.
He said that really until about 200 years ago
There weren't any cultures that viewed issues.
of mental health, like depression, schizophrenia, those types of disorders, as anything separate
from maybe demonic possession or some sort of supernatural influence.
I mean, I really agree with a lot of the things that you've talked about on the podcast
in terms of there really being no separation between these material, phenomena and the spiritual
reality. But I guess my question would be, has there been any time during the history
of Christian thought or any examples where a distinction is drawn between those two.
In essence, we see diseases, mental disorders that can be cured with medication.
Is there a way to draw a line there between what might be more material, more spiritual
or maybe just looking at this totally wrong?
Okay.
So what do you think?
I mean, there's a couple of claims there, right?
the idea that no one in the pre-modern world.
thought that mental illness was anything but what we would now think of as purely spiritual.
And then also the question of, can we make that distinction or in what way should we make that
distinction? So what do you think, Father? Yeah. Well, I mean, a lot of that depends on
there being an either or. Right. So, you know, and this is, you know, programmatic for a lot of
modern people, right? Either this is just the
product of a material system of causes or it's a miracle. Yeah. Right. It's only a miracle
if there's no, you know, material causes. And it's only totally material if there's nothing miraculous
about it. And so part of the reason why you're not going to see that distinction among pre-modern
people is that they're actually always trying to do the opposite. They're always trying to show the
connections between these things.
Right, like we're constantly seeing in the Gospels
Right when Christ heals someone there's this connection between the healing of soul and body
Yeah, right. There's just casting out demons. There's healing physical ailments and there's the forgiveness of sins all
Sort of mixed together all the time, right that these things are always
sort of intimately connected
Right, but they're not connected in sort of a crash.
way like Job's friends, right? It's like you sinned there for bad thing happened to you.
Yeah, and it occurs to me, like I'm reminded suddenly of something that St.
Nikolai Villamervic said in one of, I think one of his homelies, where he talks about miracles
and he says that a miracle is simply one of God's gifts at which men marvel.
You know that it's all God's gifts, right? That, you know, the good things that we receive are
all gods gifts but there are some of those gifts that we marvel at because
because that's just kind of the way that we are.
Right?
It's like, I mean, even within stuff that you might think of as purely quote unquote spiritual,
right?
Orthodox Christians who go to church every Sunday don't tend to go, whoa, wow, what's
happening when they know that the Eucharist has become, you know, that it's become the
body and blood of Christ.
But if they see a murder streaming icon, they're much more likely to go, whoa, you know,
even within those things that we think of as spiritual there's kind of
levels of marveling, right?
You know, like the Eucharist people tend to marvel
if they contemplate it.
It's not something that sort of smacks them in the face,
the way that a strongly visual miracle,
quote unquote, might.
But even then, I mean, there are commonplace things,
like a sunrise or a sunset.
Right, the people marvel.
That we would hold our totally material causes,
but the people will still pog out about it like.
Pog out.
Yeah.
Well
Well, you know, have that experience of on wonder, right?
Yeah.
And so, part of this is also related to this idea we have as modern people that we're sort,
you know, at best, right?
If we're Christians, that, you know, we're a ghost in a machine, you know, that there's,
you know, we are a soul which is a thing and it's like living inside our body.
And again.
That's not how it's seen in Scripture.
Human person is a human person.
It's not just in terms of criticizing a pulmonaryism, sorry William Lane Craig, that we are
you, that Christ is one person, and that human nature is one and is whole.
That's true for all humans.
Human nature is one and is whole.
And so...
You can't separate out these capacities.
We know this in experience.
There's not somebody who has spent years dealing with a debilitating physical ailment
who hasn't struggled with mental health and depression along the way and who hasn't been
subject to spiritual attack along the way.
our actual human experience, those things are never separate, right?
They're all...
mixed together and intermingled. And so I think the the instructor who who
Ben's hearing is sort of trying to to demangle these things. He's trying to say
that oh no no no they were saying it was only like this person was fine and
and then some demon came out.
Right?
That's what they thought back then.
But now we know it's right, this other thing.
But the reality is, this is the modern, you know, everybody in the past was a primitive
screwhead, right?
Right.
The fact is they had a much more nuanced view.
They didn't deny the material elements and the mental elements.
You'll find people talking about distraction at these different problems, right, and despondency
and this thing.
But they always saw those as having physical and spiritual causes and effects.
Right, it was a purely one thing, the way we modern folks want it to be.
Right, right.
Okay, so now we've got a question from Cynthia.
Hi, Father Stephen, we have a question for you.
Kind of two parts.
We are wondering if you can help us understand
Who it is, thick.
pain had children with.
And we're wondering if that might be related
to your discussion about giants.
And in Genesis chapter six,
it says now there were giants on the earth in those days,
and also afterward, when the sons of God
came into the daughters of
men and they bore children to them. Those are the mighty men of old men of renown. And there's also
reference that giants are also known as Nephilim and hybrid sons of fallen angels. So if you could
please clarify for us that would be very helpful. And thank you for clarifying so much for us as we
are listening to you.
your podcasts and starting to read your book. Thank you.
All right, so there's several things there. Number one, who is
Kane's wife? Does this have something to do with giants? And
how does that relate to the Nephilim? What do you think,
father?
Yeah, I apparently they only want to know what I have to say about it.
Yes, right? It was directed to you. So it doesn't matter.
You get a buy. I guess completely.
Yeah, no, go for it. Number one, listen to a three and a half hour
episode.
about giants. Yeah, exactly. Yeah, in terms of the giants and Genesis 6 and everything,
we got to go back to the giants episode because all the other people with questions would get
mad if we were rehearsing. But in terms of Kane's wife, we don't know. Yeah, she's not
mentioned, right? Just says that he knew her, his wife, right? Well, not named. Yeah.
Yeah, she's not named, she's not named, right.
And so, um.
Folks who want to take a very literal read of Genesis chapters 4 and 5 say, well, it must have been a sister,
which is certainly possible.
There are other people who have various theories that come under the heading of what's called co-atomism.
Co-atomism is basically just any theory in which there are other people besides
as Adam and Eve who are around.
those theories run into a bunch of problems. Now, we have to distinguish among those theories.
So, co-atomism in the 19th and early 20th century was mostly racist. I mean, very literally
it's pretty horrific. Some of the stuff you will find if you go and do it Google search
for co-adonism now that I've told everybody that term.
is an attempt to try to say that there are multiple races of humanity.
Right, and the ones you don't like are descended from cane.
Yes, so the one you do like is descended from Adam, right?
Oh no, this is co-atomism. They're not even descended from cane.
Oh wow, okay.
Yeah, yeah. You also get this sometimes in terms of different people trying to incorporate
the story in Genesis.
into various evolutionary theories, right?
So there's like a whole bunch of humans who evolved
but then God creates Adam separately, right?
The places where all those theories run into kind of a problem
is that you have to have death come to humanity
through something other than Adam's expulsion for paradise,
which we've talked about a lot in different episodes.
And if you break that connection to death, right?
if you've got most humans just living and dying
and death is natural to them,
that creates real problems on the other end
when it comes to Christ defeating death.
And the fact that everyone now today,
so there's a revised, revised, revised recent version
of this theory that's become very popular among certain
internet Protestant apologists.
where they point out that, well, even if there were these other people who evolved and
Cain marries into them and stuff, by today, all this thousands of years later, we're all
descended from Adam anyway, so it's okay.
The problem is you have a whole bunch of generations that aren't.
two-room deathless natural.
So there's a lot of problems that come.
So some kind of co-ademism in that sense,
in having some more people around,
I understand why people would find that attractive
because it would let you solve certain problems
like who's Kate's wife and some other things,
and how does he build a city?
How did there get to be that many people?
But you end up with theological problems
that are way worse than just having to say.
say, like, I don't know who Kaine's wife was, the Bible doesn't tell us.
And we have to remember that not just Genesis 1 through 11, but the whole Bible was not
written to answer our questions and our curiosity.
God has specific things he wanted to communicate to us.
And so especially if our answers to our curiosity start to conflict with or make us, you know,
You
fiddle with those things. God is trying to communicate. We've we've gone
aground with my shipwreck time. Yep. Okay. So we've got another question. This
one is from Emilia. Hello, fathers. I'm Emilia from Romania. And I have a
question about the soul. In the last episode, fathers even said that we shouldn't
think of the soul as being a thing, an eternal immortal element of our being.
Rather we should think of it as the life of the body.
Could you elaborate more on this idea?
How should we understand the afterlife given that the soul is really not the spirit you
get to wander around with when you die in a word of workraft?
And what about the process of demonization?
Because the Nephilim's soul seemed to me to get that workraft's treatment when they
possess human beings.
And also what about the Old Testament idea that the soul descends into the underworld after
death?
but that it also returns to God.
Thank you for these and for your very helpful and useful work.
Okay, so the question seems to be if the soul is not a thing, all a day card, right?
If it's the life of the body, the play-doh.
Yeah, exactly, right, sorry, yeah.
Well, you know, all philosophy is just footnotes to play-doh, as they say, right?
Yeah, you know the thing about human beings being spheres
Isn't that origin as a man who's really about the spheres?
Well, he's getting that from Plato.
Yeah.
The Tameas.
He's started out as just like a spherical head.
But then they'd roll around and fall into a ditch or something and they couldn't get out.
And so that's why bodies.
Right.
Which, you know, to carry the head around.
And in Charlie and the Chocolate Factory,
where you also have the film versions, where they won't get the chocolate factory,
you do have Viola who becomes essentially a sphere.
So yeah.
It is an originistic film, a platonic film really.
So just throwing that out there.
Okay, but so the question is that if souls are not things,
if they are the life of the body,
then how does that explain the sense of them journeying
or being parted from the body?
Like what exactly is going on there?
And then of course he mentions demonization, demonized souls.
Right.
They had a world of warcraft.
So next time you're doing a corpse run,
the spirit healer high for me.
But so yeah, so yeah, so the idea of the immortal soul is from Plato.
And when Plato says the soul is immortal, he means it.
So Plato has the trans migration of souls, aka reincarnation.
Because of something's immortal, it's immortal, in and of itself.
So, and then the body is the prison of the soul, et cetera, et cetera.
So, even though Calvin quoted that, it's not Christian.
So, if you go back to the Hebrew Bible, right, soul just means life, nephish, just means life.
So, when God creates the fish of the sea and the birds of the air,
It's the souls that swim in the sea and the souls that fly in the air.
And everyone from Aristotle to St. Gregory Pala Moss, that covers some ground, says that animals
that even plants have souls, they just have souls of a different type.
Right.
Then human souls.
And the reason you can say that is because they're alive, right?
The Latin word for soul is anima.
So we call something that is...
is not alive in an animate object, a soulless object,
as opposed to one that has a soul.
So when we talk about the soul leaving the body
in that original, herbetic context,
we're literally talking about the life leaving the body.
The body is still there, it is no longer alive,
it is now inanimate.
Right.
And so the question then becomes what happened?
to that life. And so yes, we get spatial language, right, going down into the underworld or up into the heavens, right?
But we have to take that, you know, by way of analogy, because even somebody like Plato doesn't think that a soul fills physical space, right?
or ways anything. They did those experiments.
Right.
I was about to say that.
Yeah, but you know, it has mass and takes up space, right?
So, this is part of that, you know, you don't know what it's like to be a bat, and as we've talked about,
what is what we call the intermediate state, the period between our physical death,
and the resurrection of the dead, what's that like? Well, we just get analogies in Scripture,
Because we don't know what that's like, right?
We know that our life is hidden in Christ, but what exactly does that mean?
So we believe that our life continues even as it leaves the body, that that life doesn't evaporate
into the ether. So that life continues. But it continues contingently,
right because it's still created.
It's not uncreated, right? The soul.
And so it is contingent all the way through, right? It is God who is
preserving it, and then we believe that life will return to the body in the resurrection for every
for every human.
And yeah, do I want to get in? So,
So yeah.
Yeah, I'll leave it there.
I was going to get into the relationship between the soul and consciousness, but we have other
questions to answer.
Yes, we do.
We can talk about that at some other point.
I'll say the thing that I would add with regard to his references to demonization.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, it would be simply that, you know, that life becomes demonized.
It becomes a demonized life, right?
And so that's the nature of that way of being.
Is it it's evil?
It functions in a-
demonic way, you know? And I mean, just as just as a human person who is not dead yet,
they can function in a demonic way. I mean, that's exactly like the fathers say that, right?
So, right. And parallel to the way in which the souls of the saints, most of whom are not yet
bodily resurrected, if you are, but most of them not yet bodily resurrected, their soul is
functioning in an angelic capacity.
Exactly. Exactly. Okay, so here's one from Evan. Hello, fathers. I've read about and heard about how in the ancient times
Tatic humans and penitents were not
President and the name of the church during the liturgy or rather
stood out in the narthex
or otherwise outside the nave and
And with our understanding of
a holiness by death. I was wondering if there was a connection there.
since penitence were not present where we understand Christ be present in the assembly of the people and the nave.
If you could talk about that a bit or answer if there is that connection or what that connection is, I would appreciate.
Okay, so I mean he said holiness by death but I'm sure he meant death by holiness.
Because holiness by death that would be martyrdom right?
That would be one of the martyrs who wasn't a Christian before his martyrdom, for example.
which is a thing. It's definitely. Yeah. So I mean, I haven't studied this question,
but my hot take on this would be that it does have, it is a symbolic way of expressing this question of
of death by holiness. You know, there was that the catechumans and the unbaptized don't get
so close because to do that, they're not ready for that yet, basically. Am I am what do you think?
Right. They haven't yet experienced purification. Right. Remember the, we were talking about the
the tabernacle of the
the labor is there so that when the priests come in they can wash.
Yeah, yeah. So yes, Evan, you've got that right.
Okay, so now we've got one for...
That was a quick one.
Yeah, well we're going to need some quick ones.
I don't have to ramble about everything.
You don't. I mean, you could.
No, please don't.
Yeah, so this one is from Jesse who has a very non-controversial thing to ask about.
Hi, fathers. This is Jesse Cosby.
I have a question about Genesis 3.
Um.
In Genesis 3 when God is condemning the serpent, he says that there will be
enmity between the serpent's seed or offspring between the serpent and the
woman and that reference to the serpent's seed is wondering if that is referring
to Nephilim or to the Bihima thread, to just other fallen angels who exactly
would be considered the offspring of the...
Thank you so much.
Okay, I'm reminded now.
So a few years ago, I did a speaking engagement in Louisville, Kentucky.
And I asked the pastor, Father Lexus Quarry, actually, at the time,
to take me across the river to, there's a cemetery there.
And there's a guy buried there named William Brannum, who is a big faith healer in the charismatic world in the middle of the 20th century.
And there's a whole bunch of his disciples buried in that cemetery.
And one of them who's
tombstone is not far away from his, is this massive thing that has this sort of long poem on it
summarizing all of his wackiest teachings. And one of them is this question of the Serpent's
seed. Like he has this idea, and this is out there, right, that there are the Serpent's seed that
exists within mankind, that functions as a kind of Illuminati, Kabbal or whatever, who are poisoning
the world and trying to turn everyone to destruction. So is that what's being taught and
Genesis chapter three.
No.
That's what I thought.
No, more common than that.
I mean, not common, but more common than that
is this idea that the serpent and Eve had came.
Yeah.
Yeah, well, right.
I mean, that's literally Cain's father.
Yeah, I think, in fact, I think that that's what,
I think that that's what brand I'm teaching what
is that yeah so that there's this keen line out there and then there's all
twist-to-face. Yeah yeah yeah and then you get you know bad 90s gothy fan
fire fiction out of that but as one does but yeah so really I mean the new
Testament lays this out pretty clearly. Right? Christ says to...
The people who are out to kill him you are sons of your father the devil right
Exactly right and in first John St John
It's not identifying Kane as literally the son of the devil, but he's using him as an archetype right hmm
So if we as we've talked about before
Sunship is primarily about image bearing hmm the son is the image of the father
And so
So the one who bears the image of the serpent, the one who becomes like that is his son,
right?
And those who bear the image of God are sons of God, right?
And Christ is the son of God, capital S because he is the perfect express image of the father.
Right?
Yeah, that's that's what this
seed or offspring or or
or son language is about and this is this is not something that's new in the
New Testament. Right a lot of people like they'll they'll attribute this like to
say Paul like say Paul does this huge break with the past where he says oh no
you're your sons of Abraham if you share his faithfulness right if you're like
I think Abraham and not otherwise.
Like, this is this bitch.
Everybody.
before that just thought it was ethnic. Yeah, no, right. It was like your right which of course
even though there was no concept of ethnicity, etc. And yeah, that is not the case. You find that
well, well before that it's like a temple Judaism, this idea because this is what it means to be a
sun and so yeah I mean Adam is called a son of God right and there are you know
angels were called sons of God
So it clearly is not about biological descent in any exclusive kind of way.
Okay, so this next question is from Josh.
Father's blessed.
My name is Josh and I'm from Oklahoma.
I've only known about orthodoxy for about a year now.
Would you be willing to explain or define what's met by the Kingdom of God?
We see it a lot in the gospels and it seems to play a pretty prominent role.
I was wondering if you could shed some light on that.
Thank you very much.
Okay, so kingdom of God.
I mean, so I'll just say this,
we tend to think of kingdom in the modern world
as being about nation states, right?
But really, in my sense of way it is in the scripture,
and of course, certainly the way that it is
in the surgical writings and the writings of the fathers
is that the kingdom of God is,
that a kingdom is the extension of the influence
or rule of the king. I guess all those who are under his sway and are obedient to him,
which is why you can be outside the kingdom of God by being disobedient.
So it's not, again, it's not like a state with borders or even a sort of spiritualized version of
that, but it's rather those who are under God's influence and who are being obedient to him and
doing what it means to be a citizen of his kingdom. Is there anything that needs to be added to
to
that or adjusted or corrected.
Well, sort of the other side of that.
I mean, you're right that the word kingdom
is another place where Latin and then English
haven't been kind to us in reifying things, right?
It's much more like you said, a verbal idea in a...
Yeah, although a brain or dominion.
In early English, it is the king.
I think I've mentioned this on this show before.
The king is the king.
He's the...
the kin person. So it literally is, it's about the guy who's at the center of the family
and kind of tying everything together. And so then those who are part of his kining
dome, those who are within his judgment is literally what that means are the ones that
are tied to him. So I mean, early English has it. But yeah, as you said later English,
And it's, as you said, more reified.
Yeah. And so from the
other side sort of as you said you know people who are obedient right that's
one side of the covenant the other side is that you know as we've talked about
before what the king does is establish order yeah right and so it is the the
what's the good see all the all the good words are all sort of
ramified in spacial and English like the arena or the realm or the
In which Christ is placing things in order already.
And so the idea is that the last judgment, the culmination of this is when this becomes true of all of creation.
So Christ is enthroned and already reigns, right?
That's an eternal reality.
And as we talk about before though, that then plays out in real time, right?
in the lives of actual people, right, who are finite,
therefore experience things at time, at space.
Right.
OK, well, we've got one from, it's spelled C-A-V-A-N.
I'm going to guess that's pronounced cabin,
but I'm not entirely sure.
Hello, fathers.
I was hoping to gain some understanding
on the feasts of tabernacles, which is currently
being celebrated by our Jewish friends.
So I know that it is commemorating the time between...
between Jewish Passover and Jewish Pentecost
with the Israelites wandering in the desert.
It's acting as a link between Passover and Pentecost
and there seems to be a connection
with the 40 years in the wilderness
with the 40 days of Christ being with the disciples
after the resurrection since that would be the time
between the Christian, Pesca and Pentecost.
So the church has taken up celebrating Pesca and Pentecost,
but not explicitly the feast of Tabernacles.
Are we somehow indirectly celebrating it or we don't celebrate it because it's already been fulfilled?
Any insight here would be appreciated. Thank you
All right, what do you think are we celebrating the Feast of Tabernacles?
Not right this second
No, so
Yeah, the Feast of Tabernacles and
Originally served a couple of purposes
the main
one was that one thread running all the way through the Old Testament and then that shows
up again in the New Testament, especially in St. Peter's epistles, is the idea that Israel
was not to sort of settle in the land and put down roots because of course has God warned
them over and over again in the Torah, especially in Deuteronomy.
now out here in the desert you're dependent on me right so you're sort of a
of the fact that I'm caring for you. But once you get into the land and you plant your fields
and you're vineyards and everything, you're going to forget about God and just attribute
all this stuff to yourself, your own hard work and your own ingenuity. And so we see all,
I mean this plays out all through. You have, you know, when Abraham and Lot decided to divide
the land, you know, Lot wants to go live in the city, settle there and Abraham lives out the
play.
right, intense. When you get to Jeremiah, there's apparently one clan in Judah that never
settled. They lived intense the whole time, right?
Right. And they're like lauded as like the most righteous family in all of Israel for
having done that. And this is where the N St Peter gets the live as strangers and foreigners
in the world, which is something we need to hear because we've settled pretty well.
We're pretty tough.
But the feast of tabernacles in that celebration and going to live in booths as the King James would have it
You're unsettling yourself right and you're unsettling yourself at the time of the harvest
Right you're unsettling yourself at one of the times when you would have been most settled right like
like this is the
Agricultural period which was the mark right being able to plant crops was
the mark of the settlement, right, of when they were going to forget God and their force to
sort of uproot themselves at that moment. There's also the interesting thing that I know we've
talked about with the 70 bulls, being offered for the 70 nations, where in unsettling, right,
Israel is sort of offering the
sacrifices for the nations and therefore serving as a priestly nation among the other nations.
So like the Levites then, who have been there.
Right, exactly.
That's had no land.
Right, parallel to the way the Levites functioned within Israel itself.
Right.
That's why the things are connected to the feast.
So for us, most of that stuff, a little bit of that stuff is shown up around Pentecost,
actually.
Most of it shows up around the piece.
the transfiguration. Right. Which happens during the Tavranacl celebration within the biblical narrative, right? Right. Yeah. Right. Exactly. Exactly. Okay.
We've got one now from Marcus. Hi, this is Marcus from Cornwall. I have a question about the use of a Tom Fama Kea in Galatians 520.
So it's translated as sorcery or witchcraft.
When I've asked people in the past they'll...
a pharmacia equals drugs or pharmacia equals demons. So I want to know, does the term pharmacia
as it's used there refer to or include a reference to the use of psychoactive drugs?
And relatively, were psychoactive drugs used in a ritual or religious context with which
Paul would have been familiar? I've heard it mentioned by other people, one team a
cannot let out.
and cannabis, hand-bain, and Beladonna were used in the ancient world, but I can't find much
information about their use in a religious context. Thank you.
All right. A completely non-controversial question. I think he's our first caller from Cornwall.
I think. I mean, we've had other British callers, but this is our first Cornish one.
Pretty cool. You know, the one thing that I'm reminded about is the Oracle of Delphi. Apparently,
They were inhaling something, right?
Do we know what that was?
Well, yes, that's kind of a theory.
People are still arguing about that.
OK, OK.
Well, it's something I've heard about.
Yes, but one popular theory is that there were sort of gases
coming up in that area.
Because like most of Greece, it's very
technically active.
And that
theories that some of those visions were triggered by inhaling the gases. I bet that's really healthy.
Yeah which may be true or that's one of those things it's hard to prove too.
So I mean Zack Snyder had it that way so I mean maybe.
So yeah, drugs, sorcery, I mean, are these are these all one thing?
or one thing in the ancient world.
They aren't all one thing, but the Venn diagram
has significant overlap, which is how
Pharmacaya gets its usages.
So it was very common within magical practice
to use psychoactive substances.
So part of the issue
you here with him trying to find more information is that when you get into academic stuff, there's
a pretty big divide because you know everything has to be divvy-duppin. It's subject to taxonomy
and academia. People who are talking about magical practice and people who are talking about
religious practice. Maybe the same people but it's rarely in the same place. Right.
That's irritating.
Those are sort of discussed separately.
Well, there's there's reasons why because they're not in the
ancient world, they weren't always the same practitioners.
Right. And then the further you go forward in history, right?
Like if we're going to talk about German or English folk
magic versus right, the Christian church in Germany or
England, right? Those are going to be radically. Yeah.
Because especially because they, you know, they do exist
simultaneously as-
as you said, a certain point in history.
Right, right.
And the further you go back in history,
and it's true, the more they kind of mingle together.
Yeah.
Right.
So I mean, when you go back to a lot of very early ancient
Near Eastern stuff, magic is invoking gods
that are the same gods who are being worshipped
in temples and stuff.
Right.
Yeah, then gets sort of shifted around as you go.
but
So within magical practical practice,
for the most part was always sort of a folk practice.
Right?
You wouldn't go to one of the scribal priests
in Egypt at the temple to get them to do a love spell.
Right?
There was somebody in your village who could do that.
Or who knew how to do that?
And the technique of how to do that.
Your local pharmacist, as it were.
Yeah.
That's Noah.
It's pharmacists.
Yeah.
I know of these.
It's the one who listens to this show, actually.
So there were different methods for doing different things.
And in some cases, those involve psychoactive substances.
Or just alcohol.
Right.
And other physical techniques to induce
an altered state of consciousness, right?
What?
of those kinds of things all mingle together, right? So not all pharmacaya in the sense that St.
Paul's using it in Galatians is about psychoactive drugs, but some of it is. Okay. Yeah.
Right. And there weren't a lot of people using psychoactive drugs, psychoactive drugs in other contexts
at that point in history. There weren't sort of like recreational drugs. Let's all go to a party
and drop acid, right? That wasn't.
What happened to the exact thing?
Yeah.
Okay.
All right.
Well, we have one more question we're going to take before break.
And this is another Ben.
Father's bless.
In Daniel 4 and the 18th year of Nebuchadnezzar, the Babylonian king receives a warning in a dream that judgment is coming.
He destroys the temple in Jerusalem in his 19th year and then surprise surprise judgment falls that same year.
Judge M.C. said to have been handed down by the watchers and was announced by a watcher
and a-
a holy one, or a mighty angel set from heaven in the old Greek.
Are you aware of the theory that Nebuchadnezzar's transformation was intended to depict the reversal
of Enkidu's humanism?
Enkidu was set in the mountains, with Shaji had long nails like talon, he progressively
moved toward quote unquote civilization and away from the gods until he becomes allied
to Gilgamesh the King.
And the answer was dripping away from civilization into the mountain.
His hair became long and shaggy and his nails grew like talent.
In the old Greek version, the angels are said to even feed Nebuchadnezzar like a beast.
If Nebuchadnezzar's punishment is meant to depict a reversal of enceitous humanizing,
would this be a picture of Nebuchadnezzar becoming totally demonized for a time?
Why does this make me think of the gathering de Manya? Thank you, fathers.
Well, that's pretty cool.
I was I was I was fast asleep by this question. So I mean is there a link between
the transformation of debit
kinesis and to a beastlike form
and the humanization of
in kido from
that, you know, the
epic of Gilgamesh and that related literature.
What's going on there?
So we're going to partially
punt here.
Oh, okay.
Because as you know
in our listeners probably
don't, we had a whole section
for the Halloween episode
this past year.
Yeah.
About madmen.
That we skipped because of time, frankly.
Frankly.
had to cut out because of time.
And so I think there's going to be a divine madness
episode in the future.
Yeah.
Add that to the spreadsheet, where we're going to do
kind of a deep dive into this.
But I don't want to leave it totally unanswered.
So there is a connection here.
And I wouldn't say it's a reverse.
I would say it's an inversion.
And we'll get into that more in that episode.
but the re-
The reason I refer to the term inversion is that
Incadue's humanization was seen as a negative thing.
It sort of culminates in him sleeping with the cultic prostitute
and that ends up getting him killed.
Whereas this reversal is seen as a...
It's seen as a negative thing that he becomes like a beast.
So there's-
something going on there in terms of inverting that pattern.
So, and we will go into a deep dive on that deeper dive than we could go into right now,
even if I wanted to, in that forthcoming episode.
All right.
So that is okay, spreadsheet keeper, you can add that to your spreadsheet.
But meanwhile, we're going to go ahead and take a quick break.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
New from Ancient Faith Publishing.
Orthodoxy and hetero-doxy.
Finding the way to Christ in a complicated religious landscape
written by Andrew Stephen Damick.
The purpose of this book is not to prove that Orthodox Christianity is the one true faith.
I do not believe that it is possible to prove
that, at least not by what can be written in a book.
What we are seeking to do, however, proceeding from the position of the Orthodox Christian
faith is to show that the differences between Orthodoxy and other faiths are real, and
that they are important.
Orthodoxy and hetero-doxy.
Finding the way to Christ in a complicated religious landscape.
Now available as an audiobook at audible.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
or Steven DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back. This is the second half of the show.
We're not taking calls, despite what you just heard from the voice of Steve.
But we are playing your pre-recorded messages.
This is a SpeakPipe Paloza episode, where we're just answering questions.
We got through 10 in the first half.
and now we're going to roll along with Samor.
So our first one is from Nathaniel.
Dear fathers, my question is about the nature of priestly agency during
sacramental rights. There was a story recently of a Roman Catholic priest who had
been using the phrase weave aptizu instead of i-baptizu.
And in his tradition evidently this rendered the baptisms invalid.
So what is the essence of priestly agency?
How does he represent us the faithful to God?
The issue in this story seems to be about singular.
versus plural pronoun usage.
The Wii usage might imply that the priest is a figurehead
for the congregation and the I usage.
Might imply that the priest is the singular performer
and the congregation are either witnesses
or co-participants in a secondary or subsidiary role.
But both readings can be construed as compatible
with the idea that the priest is representing man to God
and God to man.
Lots of our petitions and prayers have the priest
using Wii language in explicitly priestly functions
like Whitney's Nealing Press, et cetera.
And very few of this sacraments have...
the priest using eye language. In considering this question, I'm struck by how many relevant
examples have the priest using the passive voice, baptism, christmation, eukaryous, even ordination.
So is our conception of the priesthood that much different than the Catholic conception?
In our tradition, it seems that he's not to focus the way the story implies that he is in the Catholic
tradition. Relatedly, what kinds of mistakes can make the sacraments invalid? Thank you very much.
Alright, I mean we all, well probably not all of us, but...
There was that new story.
In fact, this is now popped up two or three times,
I think, within the past year or two
that I can recall.
Either priests or deacons within the Roman Catholic tradition.
And again, it's the same thing, using this we language
and it being declared by Rome to be invalid.
Which I have to admit, I can't quite understand that
because at the same time Rome has its Eastern rights.
Now they don't tend to use wee baptize length.
right but like Nathaniel was saying and they're using the same language we are
right because they generally are using the same rights we are which you know
for instance the servant of God John is baptized in the name of the Father etc.
And you know the other thing that occurs to me is that baptism by non-priests or
even deacons is a thing like it's considered traditionally to be truly a
baptism if it's if it was necessary if it you know setting all the caveats aside
about
what constitutes a valid baptism, you know, it does include the possibility of a layman actually
baptizing. So what do you think, Father? Who is the priest in the midst of all of this?
Yeah, and without resorting to Roman Catholic bashing.
Yeah, right. That's not what we're trying to do. But yeah, it's a interesting question.
Yeah, there's suffering themselves enough over this that we don't need to add to their suffering.
Right, yeah, yeah.
And I mean,
have to be honest there is a little absurdity to it. Right? That one word in the English language.
Right? Being said differently. You know, in one case this was a priest who they watched the
videotape of his baptism as a baby. And because that one wrong word was used, he was not a valid priest.
And so every sacrament he had ever performed was not valid. Right. Right. Like retroactively.
Yeah, I mean, it definitely...
seems to have this very strong focus on the priest himself being a sort of
absolute nexus of validity if that makes any sense. Right, right. And this
gets back to actually what we were talking about in the first half a little bit
in terms of the way in which Oficion was used in Latin in the West. But so one
of the one of the big changes.
that comes when you go from Greek to Latin,
and that ends up,
I don't wanna overstate it,
but I don't know that you can overstate this.
This ends up becoming the,
this one translation thing ends up becoming the source
of much of the difference between Western
and Eastern Christian theology.
Hmm. Um, and that is that the the wording
Greek, uh, inner yeah, uh, like the energies, right? Was, so for example, an Aristotle,
if you read metaphysics, data, it's an, uh, an ontological category. He says energies
are. Right. He has dynames and niraya. These are two modes of being or two aspects of
being, right? And by and large, it takes a little while for a Latin translation to be
settled on, but ends up being effected. The effect produced by something.
Because I know there was also what operatio is and that also used.
Yes. Yeah. Well, yeah, we can get into operatum. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Um,
Oh, bad work. It's starting
the Latin and Greek philology day.
Yeah.
Operato, it's up getting used in related but other contexts.
Operato.
The working is, again, is activity.
Right. This is a case where it went the other way.
Yeah, right. Right.
Where what was sort of a reified category,
right, an ontological category, a category of being
uh...
are, right, became a more verbal idea, right, of working, of producing an effect. Yeah. Right. And so,
you get what you get, we'll talk about both of these in the development of later
Western theology related to the sacraments and the sacraments become a fact, right?
But the sacraments themselves become what is doing the work
Right exoprooparotum right the
The sacrament itself does the work and produces the effect
Right, and then as we talked about
Ophissium the the priest is that necessary instrument
Right through which
Shhh.
the sacramental effect is worked.
Right.
And so in the West, they'd ever deny that God is ultimately,
God is the ultimate minister of the sacrament.
Right.
Because they're not donatists.
So the priest could be a heretic,
the priest could be a complete evil doer,
he could be an atheist.
Right?
In the Western system,
that it is of itself does not affect the validity
because he's...
the instrument, right? He's the through which. But the sacrament itself does the work.
And so the sac, since the sacrament itself does the work, if the sacrament becomes incorrect,
then it doesn't do the work. Right. And so if we shift, shift now to the east, right,
where we stick within our yeah, right, where we stick with this ontological category,
is directly connected to God.
We're talking about the divine energies
in the sacraments.
When we talk at the Orthodox Church
about every time, place, space,
every bit of matter in the universe,
being potentially sacrament or potentially mystery,
potentially the vehicle for the divine energies.
That's not just hippie stuff.
Right?
Hey man, the whole world is...
sacrament. That's not what that's getting it. It's that the divide energies which are
God Himself because it's still an ontological category. Right. Is working in and through
the mystery. Right. So in baptism you have material water. Right. And God Himself is working
in and through the water.
Right. God is not a...
the beginning of a chain. Yeah. Right. That passes through the its
retality of the priest. And then the water itself becomes capable
of purifying sin. Yeah. No, it's God doing that which is which
then explains why it is that a Lehman can theoretically baptize
right? Like like God himself is in the water purifying from sin.
Right. Yeah, it's not a...
water's not changed to become magical water.
Right. Yeah. Yeah.
Well, I get out of what I admit.
I mean, the term,
Hocus Pocus does come from the Latin.
You're right. Right.
It's I mean, that's a distortion of understanding of that
Hocus Corpus Mamm.
Right.
But that is the world in which that distortion arises.
Right. Yeah.
And the, the, but, you know,
again with the Eucharist.
the priest as that instrument, as the charism has the power to make it the body and blood of Christ.
And then once it is the body and blood of Christ, it performs its function, exopro-brother, right?
It, you know, anyone who receives it will receive the body of Christ.
And it's even interesting that in most modern Roman Catholic,
It's hard to generalize anymore about Roman Catholicism.
It's about as hard as generalizing.
about Protestantism nowadays. But it's interesting the whole idea of the Eucharist being dangerous
when received unworthily kind of drops out at some point. But then because it's simply now
is the body of right now you get Eucharistic adoration now you get, right? But it is now the host itself
right who is. Yeah so it's a
Objectification.
Right, right.
And so that flows out as well as a whole bunch of other things
flows out of this move from the understanding of
energy, that's related to dynamism, right?
That comes out of Aristotle and then gets used,
gets picked up by the Greek fathers,
helpfully to explain not just the knowledge of God,
which is where we usually think about it
with St. Gregory Palomas, but also the work of God in the world,
Oh
mysteries, why we don't have a set number necessarily, all of that is part
parcel of that and and the role of the Holy Spirit and the Eucharist. All of
these things sort of play out that. Right. Right. Okay, so here's our next
question. This is from Nicholas. Hello, fathers. This is Nicholas Mattier, first
time caller, longtime listener from San Antonio, Texas.
I've got two quick questions. One, during the flood did the sea creatures also get destroyed.
And two, in the life of St. Columba, a latent heat higheography from Scotland,
There's a mention of the Loch Ness Monster.
Have you read this?
And ifs or and
How does that fit in with
Monsters and how Columbia deals with this monster? Thank you fathers
Alrighty so
That's fun
I have read the life of sink Columbia and I although it's been a long time and
My recollection is that it just mentions him seeing it
But there might be more to it than I'm just simply not remembering because I think it's been close to 20 years
So I don't know.
What do you think, Father? Are sea creatures killed in the flood?
If so, then, I mean, if they were, then where did they come from?
Right? Because it's not like we don't see Noah with any aquariums on board the arc.
Yeah. So part of part of this is, you know, the chain's wife thing.
Yeah. Right. We're just sort of curious about stuff. Yeah.
Yeah, so curiosity.
Which is understandable.
Yeah, if you want to work on a real material level, well, I mean, you know, with a flood like that,
you're going to get salt and fresh water mixing together. Right.
That would probably wipe out a lot of sea life. There's going to be other environmental factors.
Right.
The destruction of habitats for different creatures and stuff. So I mean, okay.
Yeah.
The key though, the key though is that the idea of what's going on
in the flood and this becomes really clear if we back up and read Genesis 5 which we don't because
it's a genealogy and we find those boring. It becomes clear the prophecy that's given regarding Noah's
birth, right? It's through Noah that God is going to save his creation and what's he saving his
creation from humans. Yeah. Right human evil. Right. Right. So the goal of the
It was not to wipe out all the creatures.
It was to wipe out all the humans.
And Noah takes the animals to save the other creatures.
But weren't responsible.
Right, so even if all the sea creatures survive,
that's fine, the sea creatures weren't the ones
painting the world with their evil and wickedness.
Right.
A few of them, you know, will buy that and stuff,
What I mean other than that.
So what about the Loch Ness monster then and St. Columbo?
No matter how much he asks, don't give him the 3-fiddy.
Okay.
Alright.
Yeah, I mean, there is stuff, you know, if you read like St. Columbo and St. Columbo,
a lot of the Celtic scenes, there's a whole lot of stuff about facing off against demons
and this kind of stuff.
I've actually been to the place where St. Columbo supposedly saw the lock.
which is Loch Ness, which is in Northon Scotland.
There's a castle right there, actually,
Urkart Castle, although the castle,
I think is much later than he was,
but the location is where he cured,
I think it was King Brood, was the name of the pagan king,
the cured of a disease
and then converted him to Christianity.
So I don't know, it's my memory of the Loch Ness monster stuff
in St. Columbus kind of murky.
So I just don't know.
I'm not intended.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, fun fully now intended now that you know yeah, but yeah, so I mean in general in a general sense
It's important that we don't take sort of a naturalistic read of these. Yeah, right, right. Sorry, Kenham
So like when when the Loch Ness monster or another see creature monster shows up
It's not a place the sore that survived yeah, right
But locks are really deep father come on
It's not what it's aimed at right so usually and again
and I'm not super familiar.
with the details because other than Dr. Who, I'm not that much of an angle file. Sorry, guys.
It's Scotland, not England, Father.
Oh, sorry. That shows you.
That just shows you. I should have known that.
The St. Columban self was Irish.
Yeah. Well, the Scots and the Dutch have a bit of rivalry
who's stingier and more Calvinist.
So, uh, wow.
Talk about fair.
The idea is you generally that these saints are confronting the demonic powers and the
powers of chaos and stuff that are resident in these lands that they're coming to with
the gospel in a general sense.
Well speaking of Noah and his flood, here's a question from someone named Noah.
I have a question about the Divine Liturgy.
I know it's been mentioned before that it is a kind of liturgical apocalypse and that at
least the first half has its origins in the liturgical worship of the temple and the
synagogue.
But given that the synagogue doesn't really show up until after the Babylonian captivity
and isn't really mentioned much in the Old Testament, what are the origins of the synagogue
again, how or why it was sanctioned.
by God when he had previously said that worship was to be conducted at the temple only.
All right, so what's the origin of the synagogue and how does that relate to the temple and
orthodox worship? Yeah, well, so remember in terms of worship only happening at the temple,
we're talking about sacrifice. Right, no sacrifice is at synagogues. Right, no sacrifice is at synagogues.
Now the temple and elephantine island.
But...
Denta.
But there weren't sacrifices at the synagogue, right?
That's why when we're talking about the synagogue service,
we're talking about like the first part of the divine energy,
with the scripture readings singing of solves, right?
And I mean, the origin of that is the Jewish diaspora, right?
So you have the end of the Babylonian exile,
but you only have a small segment of the Jewish community
It actually comes back to you.
There's a massive Jewish population still in Mesopotamia.
There's a massive Jewish population in Egypt
where they fled before the exile.
And then you get, as time goes on,
you get Jewish families resettling in communities rising up,
sort of all around the Mediterranean
and then points further east.
And so during the exile, of course,
They didn't have a temple.
And so there had to be sort of certain accommodations, right?
And those were not easy accommodations, right?
How can we sing the songs of Zion here in a foreign land, right?
Right.
But those accommodations get made, right?
Because again, not everybody goes back.
And so synagogue is literally a gathering place.
It's a place where the Jodian community in any given place begins to gather, right?
and they can read
their sacred texts, they can talk out and apply them in their lives. They can sing
songs, they can encourage each other and function as a community within whatever
place they're in. They are sort of nation-within-a-nation, and that then
creates this idea that there is that Judeans that we translate as Jews,
You
includes people who may have never set foot in Judea in their life.
Yeah.
Right?
Because they're part of that nation, right?
Because that synagogue is sort of an outpost of that nation.
Yeah.
I mean, does a synagogue then function in some ways as a kind of community-elevated form
of the private prayer that people would be doing at their homes anyway?
Yes.
Yeah.
Yes, but doing it together.
Yes.
So that model gets brought directly over into the church.
That's how the early Christians understand themselves. They understand themselves as a nation and a people
that's not based on or tied to one particular piece of land, in which they all live.
They're all over the place, but they are the race of Christians. They are
A. people. And so wherever they're living, they as A. people gather together
right around a place of worship.
And so all of those are sort of embassies of a nation that doesn't have land in this
world per se, sorry Vatican City.
All right, so that said here is a question from Patrick.
Greetings, fathers.
This is Patrick from Cheyenne, Wyoming.
I have a question regarding Ashera as Yalway's wife or consort.
or something that was brought to my attention by a...
deconstructing Christian as a proof against most biblical claims.
I'd like to hear your opinion.
Thank you.
All right.
This is when we've heard before.
So is Ashram Mrs. Yahweh?
Where does that come from?
Is there any validity to it?
No.
Right.
But, yeah, to just lay this out briefly, there's an inscription that was found that is generally
Translate.
into English, especially translated this way when it's going to be weaponized by your village
A.D.
type, as referring to Yahweh and his Asherah.
And they say, oh, well, Asherah, this is Bale's wife.
So O.C., polytheism, they thought Yahweh was married.
So, first of all, even if that were true,
as we've said a thousand times,
If you actually read the Old Testament, right, most of the Judeans in Israelites were a bunch of pagans.
Yeah, I was just reading the end of Joshua recently and it's notable in there it says, you know, and basically in Joshua dies or maybe it's the beginning of Judges.
And it says, and essentially, you know, the people of Israel did not know the Lord their God and they fell into idolatry and they kept falling into idolatry.
into a dollar. It's very, very, very explicit in that.
So even if that is what the inscription said, wow, you found that Israelite who was a synchrotist.
Yeah, rock, horror, right?
Right.
But why that inscription would be taken to be an official statement of the religion of the
entire people?
I don't know how you get there.
That's number one.
But number two, that's not even what it says.
So, and this is, I don't want to get too technical, but...
Ashirot, the...
way it's actually written, that particular way of spelling it essentially, of writing
the word, is never used for the goddess. Right? So it takes a whole bunch of special pleading
that doesn't really work, try to get that to be about the goddess. Because that same word
is used to refer conjugated exactly that way, including in the old
to refer to ritual poles. These ritual poles usually would or stone sometimes
deliberately phallic that were used for ritual purposes. So what the
inscription actually refers to is Yahweh and his ritual pole or tree and again
you discovered in Israelite who was worshipping Yahweh incorrectly.
Right. Just like the old testament tells us they almost all did.
Right. Right. So there you go. That's quick and easy. Okay. This next one comes from our friend Pedro.
Father's Bless. This is Pedro Sarsama phoning it in from Ice Wind Dale.
I have a question about baptism and possibly an interaction with sacred geography. Although that's
my own speculation in the D'dakki.
and an early Christian text apart from that,
and in our own canonical tradition,
the preference is given to immersion
with an allowance for pouring of water,
where immersion is not feasible.
Moreover, early texts specify immersion
and living water in running water,
and then give collected water as kind of an allowance.
This is also found in early Jewish texts
when discussing ritual washing.
One thing that I'm curious.
about is the temperature of the water. In the Dita key it says, see, use cold water rather
than warm water. And so I'm wondering if you could speak to why that might be. I don't
know if any other texts address the temperature of the baptismal thought. I haven't finished
reading the 2000 page of Lucian initiation and baptism in late antiquity, early Gidea's
of an early Christianity. So maybe the answer is there, but I'm curious about this specifically
from
in Orthodox Christian perspective and one that is informed from a sacramental
non-materialist worldview. Thank you.
All right, so why is baptismal water traditionally cold? I mean I remember that
from the Dheedaki. Although I mean frankly most Orthodox churches you go to
these days if you were to stick your hand in the font, usually they've made it
warm. Don't want to shock the baby, I think it's sort of the idea.
That's kind of a shocking thing to do to a baby anyway, but yeah, I don't even try.
It's just cool.
Uh-oh.
Yeah, why is it so it specifies cold, though, right?
Yeah.
Let me also say I hope Pedro was not cosplaying his Drizzet when he made that call because otherwise
we're going to get canceled like community.
Don't need that.
We get canceled.
I want it to be for something I said live.
Not for that.
Yeah.
Well, if they've read Icewind Dale, if they read that stuff, they probably are okay with
Yeah, if you have it, don't bother everybody, but yeah, so why is it cold? What's the deal? So
this is conjecture on my part. Okay, right, and I'm going to say that because I don't think anybody
actually knows. But my bias is I always assume a pragmatic explanation. Okay, because what I found
tends to happen in churches, is that something is done for a pragmatic reason?
And then, oh,
over time sort of spiritualized reasons develop,
has there ever been legends?
Right.
Yep.
Like fanning the gifts was mainly to keep insects away.
Right originally.
Right.
So my surmise would be that this is related
to the running water thing.
Right?
Because spring water that's just coming up out
of the ground is usually cold.
Unless you're at a specific hot spring.
Hot spring.
Right.
And when you're at a hot spring,
usually stagnate.
pools, right? And warm stagnant pools breed bacteria, whereas cold running spring water
does not so much. Yeah, and you know, the capability that we now have of simply turning on
the faucet and getting water from a water heater was not so, I mean, they couldn't certainly
could heat water, right? It's not like they couldn't do that. But I know, for instance,
that a lot of early baptismal funds.
were cut into the ground and connected to aqueducts, right?
So if you took the lid off, there's always, you know,
this water is flowing through it, you know,
all the time.
So you step down into it and you're basically
in a kind of redirected river, you know,
much like the Jordan, not redirected but is a river.
But the context in which that rule comes is talking about
which water source you should choose.
Yeah, right.
Right.
And so that's how I'm interpreting it, but it's conjecture on my part.
Okay, so it's a guess.
All right, well, this next one is from another friend of the so and that's Michael
Lansman. Hey, Father Steven, Father Andrew, Reverend Mike Lansman here.
I have a question for you about the temptation of Jesus in the gospel of Luke.
I was reading the ancient Christian commentary on scripture and the selection from
origin talks about the devil tried to tempt and shoot.
Jesus because he doesn't know that Jesus is the Son of God.
Origin takes us to mean that Jesus is a Son of God.
So I was wondering if there's a textual issue there with a gospel loop.
And they also wanted to know if Origin was on to something or if this is just some speculation.
In other words, Jesus was just a man who had power from God.
And so the devil is using the temptation to sort of get him to tip his hand
the tip of his hand or to get him to a-
identify himself. Want to know what you thought about that? Thanks so much for taking my question.
And I look forward to hearing the answer.
All right. So yeah, I guess the question partly is, what does the devil think? Who does the devil think that Jesus really is?
Does he realize he's truly the son of God or that he's just some kind of elevated whatever? I mean, I always had the impression that the devil knew
who he truly was because whenever Christ encountered
demonic beings, they call him the son of the most high. So often, you know, not every time,
but they often do. So I mean, what's going on here, Father?
Yeah. So in response to noted originist Michael Lansman.
No, he's not.
Why he's calling to talk about origin?
Yeah, so I think...
it is just wrong on this one. And I think the best piece of evidence of that is there's this kind of
funny bit that people don't notice that where he mentions that you know, you shall not allow your
foot to be dashed against the stone, right? He quotes a couple verses from a Psalm and he skips one.
Okay. The one he skips is about
stomping on serpents and scorpions.
Okay.
And so he literally skips the part about like Christ stomping on him.
In his quotation.
Yeah, right.
And all right.
So that implies to be that he kind of knows who he's talking to.
Yeah.
And yeah.
Yeah, a lot of times I think the don't put the Lord your God to the test there gets misinterpreted too.
That's less like, yeah, I could jump off this building and God would save me, but you know,
I'm not going to what check, right?
Like Jesus is God, right?
Like, yeah, that's more like don't test me.
Yeah, right, right.
Right. Yeah. So I think that exchange shows that both Christ and the devil know who
they respectively are. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. All right. Well, this next one is from Stephen.
Hello, fathers. My name is Stephen, an uncle from Edinburgh in Scotland. This is my question.
In the Torah, the death penalty is imposed on those who commit certain grave sins,
on a broad lead.
for the community and the land for the contamination of sin, as in the case of the 3,000 men killed
by the Levites next to the Dersufer 2.
In contrast to this, the death penalty is not imposed in the New Testament Church.
True there are instances where God causes the death of certain people as an Iason's
Sephirah. There is acknowledgement that the state might exercise power over life and death,
and the church exercises the power of excommunication, which will be a certain kind of death is
one intended to lead to the sin as a repentance.
is crap made.
if I'm mistaken in any of this. My question is then, what has changed that means that now
the church no longer imposes the death penalty? Does it have anything to do with the Christ making
through repentance and transformation of the human person possible? Thank you and I look forward to
hearing your answer. All right, so the question is why does the church not impose the death penalty?
So first of all, Stephen, I'm sorry about that lockness thing. He's not in that part of Scotland,
and he's in Edinburgh.
So those are upcountry people.
Did I just do it again?
Yeah.
I mean, they're in Scotland, but it's another part of Scotland.
You have to go up to Inverness in that area if you want to go see Loch Ness.
Okay, but it's not that big, man.
It's true.
I've lived in California in Texas.
It's a train ride.
Okay.
Well, it is a train ride, but it's not in the neighborhood.
So the death penalty is actually imposed by the truth.
Oh, okay.
But part of it has to be how we understand
what's going on with death penalties
in the Old Testament, right?
So the first thing is that the language
that's most often used is that that person
is to be cut off from among the people.
Yeah, right.
And it's sort of ambiguous whether that means death or exile.
And the reason why that's ambiguous is that those are seen
sort of the same thing.
And the reason they're seeing is sort of the same thing.
Goes back to Genesis 3.
Right?
Because what is death?
Death is being cut off from the tree of life.
Right.
So I know I've cited this before on the show, but say John of Damascus, physical death is
the separation of the soul from the body.
death is the separation of the soul from God.
Right. And so we tend to get that backwards. We act like physical death. That's real death.
And then spiritual death is like metaphorical death. Right. And in actuality, real death
is being separated from God. Right. Physical death is metaphorical death. Oh, right. Because
what his Christ say life is.
to know the only true God in Jesus Christ who me is set.
So to not know them is death, that's real death.
So every time someone is excommunicated,
every time someone is put outside the church,
that's the death penalty.
And St. Paul uses that language about it.
You're turning them over to Satan
Satan for the destruction of their body and the salvation of their soul.
Destruction of the body and salvation of the soul, that's death, separation of the soul
from the body.
So the real death penalty is applied, but it is applied as was just suggested by that
quote from say Paul, immediately.
The idea is not the total destruction of the person.
the ideas that is the ultimate act.
to drive someone to repet.
Yeah, to bring them to life.
Right.
Yeah.
All right.
OK, so this next one is from yet another of our several bends.
Father's bless.
Somewhere in the ancient faith cinematic universe
I encountered the recommendationary
Laurie Brain, which is rituals of spontaneity.
And I'm working my through it, but I don't think
I'll be done before the episode.
So I wanted to ask, what is the role or play
of spontaneity in the Orthodox Christian life. I don't know it seems that the
maybe modern spiritualities almost deliberately skits a frenic as I'm reading
this book and not terribly certain how to maybe reframe spontaneity as it
doesn't seem to be like the chief hallmark of a life led by the Holy Spirit which
is kind of the basic understanding that came with me as a Protestant who's
seeking to become Orthodox. So I don't know it.
It seems that there's a primarily economic lens of spirituality that needs a band and an obf's curious if you could comment on that.
Okay, so the book that he's mentioning is Laurie branches rituals of spontaneity.
And Laurie is actually an Orthodox Christian. She's a professor out in Iowa.
And the book essentially shows the rise within Protestantism of the idea that spontaneity equals authenticity.
Right, and so then the the truest prayers to God are the ones that come from the heart and from the heart is understood as being about unrehearsed spontaneity, right?
It just sort of comes out of nowhere apparently.
And so Ben is asking, is that a thing within Orthodox Christianity?
Is there any role for spontaneity in in in the Orthodox Christian life?
And it's an interesting book everybody by the way. I mean, it's her doc.
digital dissertation, you know, published as a book. So, you know, don't expect it to be a super,
super light read. That's not what it is. Right. Let's do it in an afternoon. Right. Exactly. Maybe you.
But, you know, it's fascinating because this like this idea, this assumption is so built into our
modern Western consciousness, right, that spontaneity equals authenticity. But she shows how that idea has a
beginning and then you know kind of make
its way into Christian worship within Protestantism.
So, what do you think, Father?
I mean, Orthodox Christian worship is certainly anything but spontaneous.
I mean, we open books and do what it says in the book, right?
Yeah, yeah.
I'm reminded of the words of a former professor of mine who I won't identify,
but who once said, to confuse spontaneity with the Holy Spirit is strictly speaking a heresy.
But...
Well, all right.
Just strictly speaking.
But that's related to what St. Paul says, right?
The Holy Spirit is not a spirit of sort of chaos and disorder but of order.
Right.
And putting things in good order, that is what creation is.
That's important because
our culture society has very much the opposite view.
We view creativity as being the sort of chaotic activity.
Yeah, sometimes even a rebellious activity.
You've got to break away.
That's when you're being really creative,
is when you're outside all the fences
and all the boundaries.
It's when you're innovating.
And that strictly speaking again
it's not.
creativity, right? You're not creating when you do that, right? Strictly speaking,
you're destroying something that previously existed. You're deconstructing it,
right? You're breaking it down. You're twisting it around. And that strictly
speaking is what evil is. But the idea is if creating something is...
is putting it in order and that putting it in order creates things like beauty.
Right? And goodness and wholeness, then if those are the things we're pursuing as Orthodox Christians,
right, being put in right order, being justified, right, being put in right order,
putting the world around us in order, we're pursuing beauty, we're pursuing what is good
We're pursuing the wholeness.
Then the way we would pursue that is not through a kind of chaotic
Yeah
Breaking of boundaries, but through
Through good order. Yeah, but I mean isn't there a difference between I mean so there is a spontaneity that is like you said a chaotic breaking of boundaries
But isn't there also a spontaneity for instance?
There's someone who's just suddenly filled with joy right and they
I mean don't we see this in the scripture where where you know
Now clearly when St. Elizabeth meets the Theatokos...
She's quoting from the Old Testament,
who am I that the mother of my Lord should come to me?
Well, paraphrasing, I should say, right?
But still, I mean, you get the impression of
that there is something spontaneous about it, right?
That there's this sudden response of joy,
which is not the same thing as,
now let's gather on Sunday morning and do worship, right?
Or here's sort of within that spun,
it's so funny to me actually though,
that even within the kind of realms of...
of Protestantism that really value spontaneity and worship.
They still gather at specific times
and there's still tends to be some kind of schedule
and an order of worship.
Now we're going to do this and now we're going to do this.
So I don't know.
I mean, I think that there's different modes
maybe of spontaneity.
Does that make sense?
Well, but that so categorizing, for example,
that as spontaneous implies that St. Elizabeth
with the actor.
Okay, so God is working through her well or he is having an experience. Yeah
But it's not what it would be spontaneous from her perspective because it was not expected unexpected
Right like the Holy Spirit rushing upon a person. Yeah, cuz it says she was filled with the Holy Spirit right or Isaiah suddenly having a vision right
Or any prophet right having a vision all of a sudden right and then they're reacting and
and responding
into it in the moment, right?
But I don't know that that's the same thing
as in prayer or in song riffing off the top of your head.
Yeah, because I think that's the thing is,
is that those who do that would probably say,
in good faith, like really believing,
that that's what's happening as the Holy Spirit
is prompting them.
And that's where that heresy thing comes from.
Right.
Yeah.
No, but that's, yeah.
reason.
The reason a strong word like heresy would be used is
you're attributing then whatever you're saying or doing to the Holy Spirit to God himself.
Right. And how many times I know you've had this happen? How many times have you heard someone
get up to speak in one of those contexts and say, hey, I was going to talk about something
totally different, but the Holy Spirit just laid it on my heart to say this instead.
they say a bunch of erroneous stuff. Right. Stuff that is just objectively not true about the
Bible or whatever. Right. And they've now taken their own personal opinions, their own personal
failings of the study and research and attributed them to God himself. Yeah. Right. That is if we
stop to think about it. Blasphemous and worthy of that kind of strong language.
Right so I
would not be so quick to attribute my present emotional state or whatever thoughts are coming
into my head at this moment. I would be very circumspect about attributing those to God
himself in any situation. Yeah. Okay, so a complete lack of discernment there. Right. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Well, so here's one from actually it's two from Svetlana. Then the
pickassels aren't gonna like me.
Hi, fathers. Thank you for the spot.
and for the opportunity to ask questions.
I'm not sure if I can ask two questions,
but one question is my own,
and another one came from my adult son,
who unfortunately can't ask it himself,
due to the time difference.
So he delegated me to do it.
He moved to Russia, and as currently living,
then he's a student of the St. Petersburg Orthodox
Theologian Academy.
So he's my son's question.
Father De Young has said that the ancient peoples
to whom the Bible was written
would not have understood it as either LHR.
history or a pure allegory. But if that is the case, how can we as modern people correctly apprehend
the Bible? How can we conceptualize that liminal space between history and allegory and is it
accessible to modern people who are not biblical scholars? And my second question, as I said,
is my question. In the coin stood by the right hand podcast, it was stated that although the
mother of God is at the same time.
his daughter because he has been the God since the beginning and before that but
following this line of reasoning it seems to appear that Jesus could be his own
son also because he had always existed right does it make any sense or do you
have any comments thank you okay well I'm gonna tackle that second one myself
And you can um actually if me if not need be I would
Alright, alright, alright, so I would say this.
So I mean we do certainly speak of the Theatokos as being the daughter of God.
We also speak of hers being the bride of God and the mother of God, right?
But the sense in which she is each of those things is not the same sense, right?
So Jesus is her son, and there's a sense in which God is also her father,
but the way in which Jesus is her son and the way in which God is her father
are not the same.
way. So for someone to be like, I mean, she didn't put it this way, but like, is Jesus
his own grandfather? That would imply that the relationships all along the line are exactly
the same kind of relationship, right? And that's not what is being said by this at all.
And indeed, when we, for instance, refer to the Theotokos as the bride of God, we don't
mean the same way in which, you know, my wife is my bride, right? There's something analogous
there but it's not the
thing exactly. So I don't know any um actually you need to apply to that? Well there was a
actually early days of the internet, days of your. There was a film. People don't even know
what that is. Oh yes. Yes. I know what a film is. F-I-L-K. Look it up everybody.
About time travel called I'm My Own Grandfather. Yeah well there's a note. Yeah there is an old
There was a song from I think the 70s called my own grand-par with
which is some kind of comedy, country song or something like that.
Yeah.
But that's about, I think.
That's another thing.
Yeah, right, right.
But, right, so yeah, as you said in different senses, and this daughter of God language is
related to the Sun language we talked about earlier, it's your imaging.
Yeah, right.
Yeah.
And in terms of, in what frame should we take the Bible?
Yes, that's kind of the bigger question here, I think.
If you're ever going to see your son awake, your heart is in pain.
You're in pain.
I haven't told you this yet, but I'm telling everyone.
Oh, wow.
This is the world premiere of this thought.
Yes.
Next episode.
How to and how not to read the Bible.
There you go, everybody.
It's gonna be exciting.
So we're gonna, yeah.
And I am impressed by the use of the term liminal space.
Mm.
Well, he is a theological student, so.
Okay.
But yeah, we're gonna get in there to that liminal space.
Next time on Lord of Spirits.
Excellent.
So...
All right, well, that's a little bit of a punt, but it'll be next time.
So it's just a couple of weeks.
Yeah, it's a very short one.
Just a couple of weeks away.
There's spital on his son.
So just, just hold on.
Okay.
So before we go to break, we have one more question.
And this is from Tyler.
Father's bless.
My name is Tyler and I'm an Orthodox Christian from Louisville, Kentucky.
And I was wondering, what is the evil eye?
It seems ubiquitous around the world.
But I'm not clear whether it's what...
you've called the taint of sin, envy in this case, or if it's demonically animated, or if
it's literally just superstition that doesn't actually exist.
Using homicides or beads or trans protection against it seems like idolatry, and I'm
assuming the sign of the cross repair, holy water, etc. would be the true way to defend
against the evil eye if it's even something real that can hurt us.
So a broader question, I guess, could be, are curses and spells real?
Are they something like the energies of demons?
a person fall victim to them.
direct demonic participation as in the case of evil eye victims being on the
receding end of envy. Thank you for your time to answer.
All right. The evil eye that pulsating, glowing blue eye that we see. I mean, it's
all around the Mediterranean, right? Like both Christians and Muslims and and
whoever else, they've all got the evil eye stuff there. Yeah. Yeah. So what's
What's going on with that?
What is up with the evil eye? Yeah, the evil eye goes way way back. Yeah, and there's a prayer
I should mention there is a prayer in the effilogian, which is sort of the priest's book of prayers for lots of occasions, right?
There's a prayer against the evil eye in some of those effilogia. I think I've got it in a couple of the ones that I have
Yeah, so
I have not surveyed all of ancient Near Eastern literature on this
What?
So what
I know. I'm a little shy.
Not my thing.
Some future, you know, when I get another PhD, I'll do my dissertation on the evil eye
and make it probably not.
That would be the only thing you'll be ever asked to speak on from here on out if you
can.
Definitely not.
Yeah.
But the earliest reference I've stumbled upon is from what's
basically a death curse and ugaritic. So we're talking about second millennium BC.
Wow. And there's some debate about part of the inscription. Okay. So I'm just saying that to
cover my bases because I take one side of that debate. There's one particular word that's argued
about who or what it's identifying.
So, but essentially the way I take it is that there is this curse that's pronounced
against someone you don't like is directing the eye particularly of a knot.
is that real friendly goddess you talked about in the past.
incestuous wife of bail.
His sister's last wife.
Yes, I'm going to crack my father's skull open if he doesn't.
Yeah, right.
Her.
Yeah.
Sure.
Not directing her eye upon the person.
So you're essentially sicking her on them.
Yeah.
Right.
And what's really fascinating about it is that that's the main body of the curse.
But that at the end, there's part where...
you ward her eye off of yourself.
It's apparently it's expected that that person might send them back at you.
Oh yeah, there's kind of collateral damage potentially.
Right. So you have to kind of put up a shield in case it bounces back at you.
Right.
Pan.
Because you're getting her attention by trying to sick her on somebody.
And so the reason I bring that up is not just to say how old this idea is,
but that I think all the way through,
this is the core of what the idea is.
The idea is that you out of envy or bitterness or whatever are sort of trying to
sick an evil power on somebody.
And certainly people who are outside of Christ are capable of being victimized by
demonic powers.
They're subject to the demonic powers, right?
That's one of the things Christ does.
said, it's free from that. So, yes, such a kind of thing can happen, happen all the time
of the ancient world. But also, yes, trying to word that off with amulets and stuff is exactly
the kind of practice that's forbidden all through the Old Testament.
Yeah. Yeah. And I mean, I've seen, you know, there's variance on this. You know, often you see it,
the little amulets looking like an eye.
But there's also a version that's just a little blue stone that doesn't particularly look like an eye.
And you can find, unfortunately, you can find Orthodox Christians who wear these little things.
And even I've seen them brought to baptisms. And I'll say, no, you got to leave that, you cannot
bring that into a baptism. Bring the cross. Yes, we need that. And then I know there's some people,
especially Middle Eastern people that like to add icons of Christ and his mother,
here.
to the chain on which they wear the baptismal crosses.
But yeah, no blue beads, no amulets, that's no.
If you're really worried about that, right,
go and pray Psalm 91 or 90 in the Greek number eight.
Second time we've referred to it today,
but that Psalm is an ancient exorcism prayer
and is literally all about God protecting you
from various pay.
in God's slash demons.
There you go.
All right, well, we're gonna be back after a short break.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Are you curious about the...
Orthodox Christian faith.
Do you have questions about Orthodox Christianity
that you can't trust strangers in internet forums to answer?
Are you an Orthodox Christian looking for a reliable first place
to send your interested friends?
Do you need help finding an Orthodox church near you?
My name is Father Paul Hodge.
I serve in the Antiochian Orthodox Christian
Archdiocese of North America.
My name is Father Joseph Lucas.
I serve in the Orthodox Church in America.
My name is Father Anthony.
I serve in the Greek Orthodox Archdiocese of America.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick, Chief Content Officer of Ancient Faith Ministries,
and a priest of the Antioch in Archdiocese.
And we're the Orthodox Intro Team.
If you're looking for a first stop online to get an introduction to the Orthodox faith,
a place to get answers to questions from qualified Orthodox Christian clergy,
a place to send your friends and not just toss them into the chaos of the Internet,
A place to get...
help finding an Orthodox parish and get plugged into an actual Orthodox community.
Then point your web browser at orthroxintro.org.
Orthodoxintro.org is a free service of ancient faith ministries and made possible by our donors.
It's an Orthodox enramp to the Christian life.
Again, that's orthroxintro.org.
We're back now with the Lord of Sp-
The Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome back everyone. It's the third half of the Lord of Spirits.
And once again, this is not an actual call-in show.
So don't call that number. You will not reach us.
You don't know what you're reach.
It's a subject of much conjecture, but you will not reach us. That's for sure. We're both going to be
in church when this airs. So we've covered 20 questions so far in actually by the time we get to
this third half, we'll probably be out of church technically. Yeah, that's probably true. That's
probably true. But let's be honest. That's true. Yeah. So all right, well, we are in the third half.
We've done 20 questions and let's go ahead and roll on to the next one so
one is from Will. Okay, Father's, I had a question about just this whole idea of reenchantment
and the sacramental life, and I was wondering, is it possible to enchant or kind of sacramentalize
technique, specifically pure mathematics or the physical sciences.
And if you were to do that, what would that look like?
Thank you very much.
So re-enchanting pure technique like math or science.
Yeah, is that a thing?
What do you think, Father?
Yes.
Okay, no.
Come on, let's move, let's move.
Lightning round.
Yeah, I mean you can enchant it.
I mean, if we understand enchantment, right,
in the way that we have generally talked about it on this show,
which there's a bunch of different ways to use the word,
but the way we've generally talked about it
is in terms of, like in our blur
but the beginning of every show,
the union of the scene and the unseen,
bringing the presence of Christ into everything.
Yeah, of course, right?
Of course.
Yeah, the way I talk about it
is making your weapons more powerful.
Oh, yes.
Stones and jams and...
plus plus five lab beakers. Yeah, I've been for reasons I've been reading
Simone Veil and she actually talks about this in an interesting way because
she kind of contrasts the way and this is written in 1943 the way that science
had become an idol.
because it had become an end in itself, right, rather than something that points to something
of greater and ultimate value.
And she could trust the way science was already being done at that time.
Of course, this is also during World War II.
So there was Nazi quote unquote science, right?
and contrast that with the way science.
and math were done by the Pythagorean's.
And by Archimedes and the ancient's in general, right?
Whether we're talking about ancient Babylonian mathematics
or ancient Greek mathematics.
And they saw what they were doing in both math and science
science as discovering something.
in the universe far greater than humans,
that they were uncovering and discovering
that were things of sort of divine beauty
that showed sort of, you know,
the handy work that lay in the background
right of the universe and created things.
Right.
Which is probably a little bit easier to do
with some sciences like CS astronomy.
right? That's kind of the obvious one. Right, but even with mathematics, right? I mean, she talks
about, I mean, these discoveries like figuring out you could put a right triangle within a circle
and the ratios of the angles, right? These sort of beautiful symmetries in mathematics and that
kind of thing. I mean, even, and this goes even up into the medieval period, right? The idea that
It was sort of a spiritual reality behind music.
And music is just sort of implied math.
Right.
In musical intervals, which basically mathematical intervals,
there was either goodness and beauty or the opposite with certain ones.
That were forbidden.
Right.
They sort of conjured or evoked a kind of negative spirit.
And so that's a very different way of pursuing mathematics or science.
science.
then trying to create cheap consumer products,
or using mathematics and science
instrumentally toward an end,
like using technology to sort of shape culture,
using technology to enrich yourself,
using technology for power and control.
But we're talking about social media now or what the Nazis were doing to make weapons
of destruction.
Just looking at temporary example to her, Robert Oppenheimer, there's a certain beauty
in covering the secret of the atom and being able to split it, being able to generate
an infinite amount of power.
Then you can also use that as a weapon.
Yeah.
you know, and drop it on thousands of unsuspecting civilians.
I was just saying it wouldn't be a, it wouldn't be a Lord of Spirits episode if I didn't get
to drop at least one Tolkien reference.
But I was just reading, like I was just reading chapter four of the Hobbit because I just
recorded an episode of my other podcast, which is a different podcast.
I'm in stool about that chapter.
And it's actually interesting in there is the first time in the legendarium where you
Meet goblins or or
works. And Tolkien actually has this little discursus in there about how much Goblins love,
they love clever things but not really beautiful things. And he mentions even that weapons
of mass destruction are probably invented by Goblins, you know, even the ones that exist
in his time, right? So he gives a very deliberate attribution of the use of technology in
that way to his race of almost puri.
right? Yeah, yeah. And so, I mean, mathematics and science just as much as language and poetry
can be a way of discovering and conveying a reality that isn't purely material.
Yeah. And we're that way for most of human history,
until the modern period when they like everything else.
stripped of, right? Got stripped of the spiritual help. Yeah. Okay, so our next question is from Alex.
Hey, fathers. This is Alex from Tampa. I so appreciate your show and I guess I still have some
questions after the Revelation episode you both did. I guess the second judgment is a question I have
and many of those I need have for those in...
Paradise does the second judgment do anything to those already in paradise
To those in tradition is a second judgment meant to be for
That period where the church militant and the church triumph and are praying for those in tradition that they may be redeemed
I guess the you know, we understand that there's a first
Judgment for us when we when we die when we repose
But I guess I'd like to hear some some more
we're expounding on the second.
and thank you both for everything you do in this podcast.
It's fantastic.
God bless.
Okay.
So this is, you know, touching on what we've referred to
as a two-stage eschatology, right?
There's what happens to you immediately when you die,
and then there's eventually the final judgment,
the general resurrection, all those kind of big,
solidifying events at the end.
So he seems to be asking like,
what does that second one actually do to people, right?
What's the difference from there on out?
movie.
see this in Matthew chapter 25, right? That's the last judgment, right? Right. That's, and that's
sort of a reverse, the question is sort of reversing the reality, right? In the sense that what's
being called here the second judgment is the actual judgment, because judgment, again, is not
rendering a verdict on people. Right. Right. It's putting things in their proper order. It's
putting things right. And that judgment at Christ's glory is appearing is when everything is
permanently, permanently, eternally set right and put back in order. Right. And so that's the actual judgment.
Right.
To even call the other one a judgment, you have to shift the definition of judgment.
Yeah. I mean, it's often called the particular judgment. Right. I've heard that that phrase. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, but even that is coming out of a Western view of what judgment is.
Oh, I'm more juridical right where both of them are this juridical thing about the fate of humans. Yeah, right
Right, you go to heaven you go to hell right?
That's and again, that's not really what judgment is so
What happens at that point is really a continuation of this life right?
Right, let him that is unjust beyond just you know still let him that is right just be righteous still
which I can always hear Johnny Cash
singing that in my head.
Yeah.
Is that the song when the man comes around?
I think that's what it, yeah.
That's a great song, great song.
Yeah, and so that's what that is, right?
And it's precisely because the judgment hasn't happened yet
that we continue to pray for those who in their lives may or may not.
I'm freezing it that way deliberately.
Right because we pray for people who from our perspective were good Christian folks, right?
Right but we don't know. No, we don't. We just see what we see. Yeah
And we pray for people who from our perspective were maybe rotten folks
Because we don't know right?
But we could continue to pray for them in part specifically because that judgment has not taken
Place yet. Yeah, yep
Right.
And so, yeah, so that's, I mean, he didn't make up this terminology.
No.
He's inherited it, right?
Right.
But part of the answer to the question is breaking down that terminology.
So what that, what is being called to the question of the second judgment does is it sets
all of creation are right. Right? So that the right just
dwell with Christ forever. Yeah. Yeah. So all right. Well, our next question very brief comes from Adam.
Hello, Lord of spirits. My question is, did the devil fall after creation? Do we know when the devil fell?
Thanks. You know the way he started that off, he said, hello, Lord of Sp- I mean, he's literally
addressing Christ. So do
We have to answer this question or.
No.
Yeah, did the devil fall after, I mean.
Yes.
Yeah, right.
Yeah, because he's part of creation.
He doesn't exist before creation.
Right.
I think he was referring to the creation of the world.
Or, right.
The answer to which is also yes.
Yeah.
I mean, we see him fall in Genesis 3, right?
And, and, you know.
Just because you know people have been listening for a while now. I'll just I'll proof text this right
It's and that's if you read
For example say Andrew Cessaria his commentary on Revelation when he talks about Revelation chapter 12
Scribes the dragon and the third of this stars and all of that
he says and
Extra-face own dr. Jeanne Constantine did a good translation of it
Oh
Now I have to say there's another English translation not as good of a translation, but a much nicer looking book. Oh, not Dr.
Jeanne's fault. Yeah, translation is it a series and so it has the trade dress of the series, but
There's a hardcover that's fancy looking and looks nicer, but not as good of a translation. Anyway
And in in that section of the commentary
say Andrew says we must accept as the father
have taught that after the creation of the world the devil fell through in me.
Well, there you go. That's pretty good.
And so that's the sixth century he's looking back at the preceding church fathers of which he had more of their writings than we do.
And how he summarizes it.
Yeah.
So there you go.
Okay, so this one is from our panoply of bends.
Father's Bless, my wife and I are going to our last Catechism class on March 6th and Father Stephen and recently
I'm going to do one of the part case.
that catacasms are not supposed to be about swapping out an old set of propositional
realities in order to take on the orthodox set, but it seems to imply that it's
ideally something more, and I was hoping that you both might be able to be willing
to comment or expand on that vision of what catacasms ideally is, not so
that I can criticize my own or anything like that, but having come from a low
church background where it goes like listening to the sermons is the
I found that it doesn't seem to radically change our lives and trying to work it out.
I encountered Rich Mullins who pointed out that the information age seems to lead to
this belief that if we just have the right information, we'll believe the right thing
and that doesn't work.
But it's that about being connected to a great God who really is life.
So that's kind of some of the threats even of coming into orthodoxy.
But I work at a homeless shelter and the program we do, I guess you could call it catechism
for the home lesson.
We're trying to empower them to address the chaos and brokenness in our lives, which is at your feet.
Their capacity for self responsibility and their weapon relationship.
So I was just hoping you might be willing to comment ideally on what kind of is so that has for those of us who maybe have opportunities to extend that in other areas of our lives.
Thanks.
All right.
I mean, it's a great question.
I mean, he, he mentions that he's helping to form homeless people at the end.
I mean, to me, he's got a beat on what...
what I think catacism needs to be.
And I mean, I saw this,
so I mean, I did parish ministry for 13 years.
And for a lot of those years,
I did catacism in kind of the conventional way,
which is, here's some information
that you need to know about Orthodox Christianity, right?
Here's what we teach, here's what we believe,
here's what the services are and all that.
And that information is super important, for sure.
But the question that I ended up asking
and trying to redirect catacas-
towards, especially towards the end of my time in pastoral ministry was, okay, so what
to me as a pastor is an ideal parishioner, an ideal Orthodox Christian, and how would
I teach someone to be that?
And that's different from being able to pass essentially a freshman level course in Orthodox
Christianity, right?
it includes teaching.
people how to pray, how to fast, how to give alms, how to keep silence, how to meditate,
how to see what the church's prayer is really for and what it does.
And sadly, I think that that's fairly rare or is kind of a secondary effect of a lot
of catacism that's going on these days that a huge amount really is still just giving
information and I don't fault.
people doing that because largely they're just doing the thing that they were taught to do.
But I also think the fact, I mean, let's just face it, right? We've got a big
loss of Orthodox Christians here in America generationally. And I don't know if that's in other
places in the world as well, maybe. And so clearly what was being done with those people did not
result in their long-term participation in church life.
So yeah, I mean, I do think that catacism is much should be about forming people into
Holy people like teaching them this here's your tools. Here's how you do this thing showing them how to do it and then you know
Staying with them. I don't know father's anything you wanted to add to that or adjust or correct or whatever
Well, yeah, I mean it it's related to
to a bad idea of what education is.
Yeah, right, right.
Right, because cataclysm is a substance.
of education really, right?
And this is not actually how education is done
and how it actually works,
but a lot of folks think about education is like,
well, we have this information,
we have this knowledge,
we're going to do it harder to you.
And now you're educated because you don't possess it.
Yeah.
Right? And so if I give you the lecture,
I lay out all the information,
I give you a test,
you regurgitate the information,
okay, now you know the information,
You...
For size 7.
accomplish the task of education.
And even like citizenship in the United States works this way.
If you, there are always these things where they point out
that if you come from another country to the United States
and you want to become a US citizen,
you have to take this test.
Right.
And all these questions about American history and civics
and all this.
And the thing is always 99% of,
Americans who are born here can't pass it right right in a million years
um
And
The same is frankly would would be true if we did the same thing in most of our parishes
Right
If we gave a quiz to them based on the stuff that we teach in a catacombs class of the US
You know can can most of your parishioners who haven't been through a catacombs class or even those who have if it's been a while
Give you the date.
of the ecumenical counts, right?
Or how many there are even in some cases.
Yeah.
And that kind of thing, right?
That's not what makes you part of the community.
That's not what makes you an American.
That's not what makes anyone or a culture and community.
But you look at how education actually happens, right?
A little sub-rosa beyond what we talk about, right?
So post-World War II in the United States,
How is education structured?
It's not a coincidence, right?
Kids have to show up in a certain place at a certain time.
They have to sit behind a desk for a certain period of time,
until they get a break.
Then they leave their desk, they go take their break,
and they have to be back on time.
Then they get a lunch break.
Right.
And then they go, it was setting them up
to be office workers.
Yeah, exactly.
That's what was happening at edge.
It didn't matter what you taught.
The information was not what was important.
And how much retention of that is there, really?
Right, you were in...
Yeah.
forating them, right? To go and have an office job. And the reason you didn't need education
to work that way before the war is that's not how people were working. People were going
at getting apprenticed, right, in trades and that kind of thing. That's how education took
place because that was preparing them then to be an adult and have a job and be, so,
Catechism in the same way needs to be about, and this is what it was about in the early church, right?
The length was based on the repentance needed,
the change of life that was needed,
not about how much of the internet
and how many books they had read.
It was about how much change was needed in their life.
And so it was about inculturating them
to make them ready to become adult Orthodox Christians,
who are gonna live an Orthodox Christian life
and function within the community of the church,
and how long it was,
and what needed to be talked about was all based on that.
What?
each person needed to get to that point. Yeah, how to be faithful. Yeah, and the whole
sponsorship godparent thing too was originally like a legit mentorship.
Right. Anyway, so it would be a print test, right, in a career.
Yep. Yep. Okay, so this next question comes from Steve.
Greetings, fathers. This is Steve from Grand Rapids.
Michigan. First I just wanted to say thank you for the show. I've been curious about and have felt
drawn to Orthodoxy for many years but this podcast finally let the fire in me to actually go and
participate. So thank you for that. My question is about Yam, the Hebrew word for C. I took some
biblical Hebrew way back in the day at a very liberal liberal arts college. The professor loved to
try and scandalize the students by pointing out all the places, modern translations, demithologized
the text.
I never quite had enough of a grid for how to deal with his critiques.
But thanks to this podcast and also shout out to Jonathan Pigeot as well, I now feel like
I do.
One of my professor's favorite examples was what he called Yam, the Seagod.
It seems that any time the text would say the word Yam, he'd wink and eye and chuckle
to himself.
So I'm curious about the connection between Yam, the word for sea, and more explicit references
to Leviathan and Behemus.
every
reference to the CE reference on some level to these lesser gods. Thanks, love the show.
Okay, so, Yam, when we've mentioned previously on the Lord of Spirits,
is every reference to the CE actually reference to Yam the CE God or how much can we,
this is my addition, how much can we distinguish the two in the biblical text?
right I mean this this even
goes back to all the way back to, I think it was our very first question. And that's,
see, we've got this either or. Yeah. Like, how do we tell if this is referring to the
water, right, the H2O with a certain saline content, that large collection in the Mediterranean,
And how do we know when it's referring to the God?
And it's always...
referring to both. Because for ancient people, those weren't separate realities. So calming
the sea then is literally putting yam to rest, so to speak. Right. Yeah. Right. And so you
can't talk about a thing without talking about the spirit of the thing and you can't talk
about the spirit of the thing with that also talking about the thing.
Right. So and the remember as we talked about way, way back in one of the early episodes using
Philo as an example. Ancient Judaism, ancient Israelites and early Christians did not disagree
with the pagans. There were spirits related to everything. They disagreed about the status
of those spirits.
Yeah.
And how should you relate to them?
Right.
Yeah.
Where?
you know, like we pointed to Philo saying that those gods even calls them gods for a small G
gods. He says those are not gods to be worshiped to their own right. They're part of V gods
administration at at various ranks. But yeah, there is that dimension to all realities.
And I'll just touch it here.
I avoided veering off completely into this earlier,
but just to touch on it here.
And since Peshau was mentioned.
One of the times I talked to him,
this bit got clipped out about cities
having souls and people lost their minds.
Which, hey, it makes it all worthwhile.
But the idea there is that first of all,
cities have a collective life,
but also the fact that something...
as a soul, so we're talking about with animals and plants, doesn't mean they have a human soul.
It's not the same thing. Right. Right. But there are spirits. There are power spirits about of
families, clan, cities, nations, right? Assigned to them. This is one of the basic things,
sort of all through scripture. And those spiritual realities, those souls or those spirits can
and be holy or they...
can become demoniac.
Right.
Nazi Germany would be an example of a
corporate becoming demoniac.
Yeah.
Right. The giant clans.
Right.
The Assyrians from most of their history.
This can happen.
Right.
And so we sort of cut off that idea to our peril.
peril. And it's really
inadequate when when the chips are down even the most hardened materialist knows that there's
something inadequate about it that just oh I'm whole bunch of individual people made bad decisions
right doesn't cut it to describe real evil when it manifests in the world right right
Okay.
Yeah.
Yep.
Okay, so this next question is...
are final question from one of our many bends.
The ultimate thought is, plus, my name is Ben and I may most of the time listener in one
time telegram pre-order sender and don't banish me for that.
And have a question about the Orthodox understanding of small R revelation.
And I have a somewhat charismatic evangelical whatever that is background and was encouraged
at least then to daily be asking God.
for revelation and learn to discern whatever forms the revelation takes, whether it's dreams,
prophecy, visions, words and knowledge, etc. With the idea of being learning to grow and
discerning what God is saying to you and what am I going to do about it. I do want to add at
least that in my experience, the belief was not that these small R revelations had the authority
at all of scripture, but were more like touch points for obedience or I'm like a daily outworking
of a now here.
quotes, life led by Holy Spirit, close air quote.
I've been going to Divine Liturgy for a few months now,
and haven't heard a single sermon
exhoring me to do that, or sorry, homily.
And I'm hoping to start Catechumon class this soon,
but I was hoping you might be willing to expand a bit
on the Orthodox understanding of revelation today
and how or if I should seek it or,
and quote again, I guess, move in those gifts, so to speak.
And all those to quote.
So yes, thank you, hope to hear from you.
Peace.
All right. Well, we've heard some of that kind of stuff before. I'm suddenly reminded there
was one time when I was talking with my wife about that whole sort of charismatic-ish world,
and it's functioning along those lines. And she was not raised with that. I was raised
even gelical, so we weren't charismatic, but certainly charismatic adjacent in some ways.
So people's talking in that way was totally normal in my...
upbringing. But I remember I was trying to explain it to her and so she said to me,
she said, do people think that like God tells them to tie their shoes in the morning? Like that was her
way of putting it. And while I think most people would not have a revelation related to shoe tying,
there does seem to be for sure this idea that I feel strongly about something, or here's a good
thought that I have. And so this is God specifically telling me to do
this or encouraging me to do that.
And I even still, I mean, you and I have both gotten emails where people said, well God told
me to write to you or the Holy Spirit told me to write to you or something like that.
And I don't know if for me, I have, it's not a reaction against that, but I tend to kind
go, well, you know, it's not because I'm skeptical that God speaks to people, but
That I guess the way that I think of it is that people expect God to be a micro manager
You know in their lives. I don't know. I'm making any sense
Yeah, man the panic oscillas are all gonna hate me
He said that earlier. I think yeah
Yeah, well, I mean
Double and down. I mean really like it's funny when we when we did when a several episodes ago
I can't remember when it was when someone called in with a question about speaking in tongues
Thanks.
And we didn't really have anything positive to say about that.
We got several emails from people kind of shocked that we turned out not to be panochostles
and it's like we never pretended to be on board with that way of believing and thinking
and practicing.
But everybody is welcome to listen.
We're very happy you're here.
Whatever your background is.
Whether you agree with us or not.
Yeah.
I frequently pray for those who hate me.
So if you're hating on me, it might work out okay for you.
That's right, it's a special category of prayer just for you.
Yeah, yeah.
That's a big category for me.
But anyway,
part of the key here is that
revelation in general, right?
Like let's talk about biblical revelation.
For us as Orthodox Christians,
biblical revelation is not a series of logical propositions.
Right.
It's that sort of...
of and this is a place where we differ from some Western Confessions. I'm not thinking of the
Pentecostals now. Now the Calvinists are going to be mad at me. But the Bible is not as good.
The sort of logical propositions that sort of truths about God or Christ or salvation.
So it's the revelation of Christ who is God Himself.
Yeah, and so
When, I mean, obviously, in the most direct example of saints who have had personal
revelation in the Orthodox Church are those saints who have had the vision of Christ
in His uncreated glory.
But no, that's a vision of Christ in His uncreated glory.
It's not Christ appearing to them and telling them.
is the person you should marry. Right. Right. Or any other discursive content. Right.
And so when we were talking about Revelation, we're talking about Christ's self-revelation,
because it's all oriented toward the person of Christ. Right. So that means we shouldn't be looking
if we don't have that kind of discursive revelation in the Bible. We shouldn't be looking for that kind
I'm just...
cursive revelation in our life.
Hmm. Right.
That God is going to individually come to me
and tell me some logical proposition.
Yeah, I guess probably the point where a lot of
pentacostas and cheresmatics and evangelicals and stuff
would like where they're going I think with this is they
see for instance, particularly in the Old Testament.
God appears to someone and says,
now I want you to do the following.
Right. That's a thing in the Old Testament for sure.
Right.
and Jesus certainly gives gives
man's in the New Testament, right? So that's what they're expecting on some level. But of course,
barring the Lord appearing to them visually and saying, now go do the following, it tends to be
filtered then through, I have a strong feeling, or this makes sense to me.
Right. Right. And those are two different things. But even then, even then, the primary revelation,
right like Isaiah doesn't receive some kind of new knowledge
Right.
God reveals, Christ reveals Himself to Isaiah, and then Isaiah is sent to do something.
Christ reveals Himself to Saint Paul, and then Saint Paul is sent to go preach the Gospel.
Right.
But so there's also, and I know they're not going to want to hear this, are pedocostal
Fred's. There's also a heavy dose of Calvinism here.
There's a view of divine providence in the background of this.
Which is that God has a specific will for like every decision you make.
Yeah, right.
Right.
And if you make the wrong one, that's a sin.
God has a person he wants you to marry or not.
And if you marry someone else or don't marry that person or marry somebody and you weren't
supposed to get married.
You're like sinning.
And so you have to find a way to sort of divine
whether you're supposed to be married
and who that person is.
And this puts people through agony.
Yeah, right.
There's the whole, it's funny.
Like what is God's will for my life?
I'm like, well, actually it's pretty straightforward.
God's will is that you repent of your sins
that you love your neighbor,
that you love him above all else,
that you worship him and remain faithful until you die.
That's God's will for your life.
and anything that's actually lining up with...
that congratulations you're doing God's will.
Right, and Calvinism at least sort of puts the Ipromotor
on whatever happens.
Yeah, that was God's will.
Right, whatever happens that was God's will.
But this is projecting it out into the future
and you have to try to discern it.
Yeah, right.
And the truth is, if people don't want to hear this,
the truth is there is not one perfect person
for you out there to marry.
And that's good news because if there were, they'd probably be in China.
It's the odds based on the world population.
And you'd probably never meet them.
Right.
The reality is there are a bunch of people out there who, if you dedicated yourself to it,
you could have a successful marriage with.
And there's a much bigger group of people who you couldn't.
But I mean, didn't the Proclaimers say they would go the whole wide world just?
find her, who just defined my wife and I are America's sweethearts.
Perfectly made for each other.
But for most folks, right?
Right.
There were actually several possibilities.
And that's very unromantic notion.
But the same is true of every other decision you make in your life.
Yeah.
Right.
There are multiple things that you could eat for breakfast or lunch or dinner that would be fine.
Yeah.
Right.
they would follow the fasting rules even and it would be good.
There are other things you could eat that would not be good.
Right. And I think that there's often there's this sense that there's one right thing and everything else is wrong.
And yet the truth is, the truth is for most situations in life, there's one or two wrong things and then everything else is right.
You know, for, you know, like, that holiness actually is infinitely interesting and creative,
and it's evil that is banal and limited and rest...
restrictive. You know, I think this idea that God is
micromanaging every single decision flips it. It's, and it's,
it's, like you said, it causes a lot of agony for people.
Right. Yeah. It's, it's, it's, uh, it's Plato, right? Yeah. Yeah.
And so the discernment, the discernment is not, okay, I
have to make the decision. I have to figure out what it is that
God wants me to do.
What choice He wants me to make.
The discernment is coming to know Christ and then based on that, discerning what you should do.
Right.
What is the right thing to do in this situation?
Like if you understand the principles of bodily health, you can make a good choice as to what to eat.
Right.
And what you shouldn't eat.
Right. The question is, is this good?
Is this action good?
not is this the one good act?
that I could possibly take.
Right.
And so you can, that's where the discernment is making good choices.
The discernment is not trying to discern and figure out which available choice has the
divine impromotor on it without knowing.
Okay, so this one is from Mary.
So my question is about death and my dad recently passed...
He had passed away.
He was not a Christian.
He had made many mistakes.
He was suffering from cancer, but he died suddenly from a heart attack.
And I had been kind of really struggling with that since then, especially since.
I didn't really put a lot of emphasis on his caring for his salvation and caring about
his afterlife.
I definitely thought I had more time and I was waiting for him to move to be near us.
It was been very
devastating loss for me. My priest told me to pray for him using the Jesus prayer and I do that whenever I think about it.
And often on my prayer rope I will use that to pray for him.
Last week on the morning of my son's birthday I had a dream and the dream. It was kind of like my dad reanimated.
His head was kind of like on this stick sort of and then also he was kind of warming up his face moving and around and kind of reanimating
and his whole body appeared and I gave him a hug
and it was a very long hug.
And it felt very real, everything about it, and he seemed okay and well.
And I wasn't sure what we really believe as Orthodox Christians about the afterlife,
when we prayed for somebody who did not know God, how that person fares after they pass.
All right.
Well, what do you have to say to that father?
Well, I mean in terms of the dream we've talked before about...
how you sort of discern those kind of things by their fruits. Right. Right. So if that dream brings you
a sense of peace and comfort, right, then then that's a good thing. Now that doesn't mean you just,
oh, he's fine, I can stop praying for him now. Right. Right. Like you would never do that for a living
living in this world person. Right. Right. So, you know, you continue to pray for him. And if you have
something like that that brings.
you peace and comfort, then that's a good thing. But we can't, we're not going to get like an
objective. Right? And I know we all want that. Like, I want to have a sense of assurance in my heart
that this other person isn't heaven or is going to be on the right side of things at the judgment,
Right now we want to phrase that.
I want to be sure of that for this other person.
And that doesn't really come most of the time.
Yeah, we just don't know about this.
There's very rare cases.
That isn't something that we should be worried and upset about, right?
Because as much as we love another human,
God who created them loves them more.
And so we continue to pray for people,
But that has to be combined with...
trust in God that the judge of all the earth will do right, and that we can trust God with
that person, right? That's where the that's the only place the assurance comes from.
You're not going to get something more than that. It insurance has to come from
trusting God. Yeah, because I think that
it, you know, for most of us probably, if an angel and we were convinced it was truly
angel showed up and said, you know, your father is fine and he's going to be fine. For a lot of us,
I think that would, we would stop praying for them. Right? Like, well, I mean, I had a revelation
that he's just fine. Right? So I think that that's, if someone had to ask why we don't get that kind
of assurance, I think it's because it helps us to be faithful that we don't have that sort of absolute
epistemic. I know for a certain this is the way it is kind of knowledge.
Right. Yeah. And even then we could fall into doubt. Was that really an angel? Was that a demon trying to trick me?
Am I remembering correctly? You know, yeah, yeah. Yeah. Right. Okay. I hope that's helpful to you Mary. So here's the next one. And this is from Caitlin.
Hi, fathers. This is Caitlin calling from New Orleans Louisiana. I have a question about the Theotokas.
First, how should we understand the Theotokus' title of Panakiyat?
or all holy, specifically in light of biblical passages, such as Romans 3, which states that all men have sinned and fallen short of the glory of God.
Second, what does the tradition of the church teach about her title of Panagia? And how can this deepen my understanding of the gospel?
Thank you for taking my question.
Okay, so yeah two parts, right? How can we call her panayia all holy when the scripture says that all have sinned and
you know, what is the church's teaching about this, about this title? I mean, with regards to the
second, I don't know that there is a dogmatic teaching about it, right? I'm sure some scenes have
reflected on this, but I don't know that I could point to something and say, this is the teaching
about this title in the way that say Théautocos, right? There's a very clear dogmatic teaching about
that title. But Panagia is something that we call her. We call her all holy. And I don't think that
But that's contradictory with the scripture that's...
that all have sinned. What do you think, Father?
Yeah. So I think we need to separate the idea of holiness from the idea of sinlessness.
Yeah. There's also teachings of the church regarding the Theotokos sinlessness.
Sure. But that's a little separate from this title. Right?
the all the all holy one right so we
call the ecumenical patriarch is all holiness. Yes.
Para yota dos. I'm not, I'm not going to name any names, but
some of them have been sinners. Right. Right. Yes. Along the way,
right? The story is for one. Right. So holiness remember at
And it's sort of core...
just talking about being set apart for a special purpose.
And so what we're saying about the Ecumenical Patriarch is that he is a human
who has been set apart for this most special purpose, this most special service in the church.
And we're saying a similar thing about Paia that she was from her, well really for a conception,
but from her birth to her death, she...
was set apart. She was devoted herself entirely to God, right? Her son. And so the importance
of that title is then that it also represents a call to us, right? To likewise devote ourselves
to the service of Christ.
rather than all the other things that we can devote our time and attention and focus too.
Yeah yeah. Okay so this one is from Catherine. Hi fathers this is Catherine from Canada and the
great white sephone. I was wondering if you could tell me what the heck is going on with Samson.
the guys in absolute
savage and I just see a connection with him. The pillars falling in that he he does that and
it's rocks obviously and then if it's a connection symbolically to Cain with how in the book of
Jubilee said his house falls in on him which I'm assuming is stone and then if there's a connection
there with with the watchers and being buried underneath all these rocks and under the mountains
and things and if there is something that is...
being transmitted that way. If you could explain that, that'd be amazing. Thank you.
I have to say number one, I love the fact that she says she's from the Great White
and the Zafone. And the fact that she describes Samson as an absolute savage. That's just great.
I didn't know bail lived up there. Right? Apparently bail lives in Canada.
That's where we already mentioned in Peugeot. Can you confer?
They're right. I mean this is what Catherine is saying so
Yeah, I mean, it's it's well for those who may not know I mean obviously we've talked about bail in the past and how bail lives on
Monsafone but but in I think just within the Hebrew Bible generally right isn't the phone just kind of the term for the North.
Yeah, it's the word for North. Yeah, right, right. So she's making a very funny pun.
Now that you've explained the joke.
I'm an explainer of jokes.
Can I say?
I live with four small people.
They need to have jokes explained to them sometimes.
It's just a habit. Yeah, that's true. That's true.
Is there something that she's got going on here?
You know, she talks about Samson being buried under rubble.
And I think it was she said in Jubilee's Canes House falls in on him.
And then there's this reference to the watchers being buried underground.
Is this a deliberate symbolic parallel going on here?
Yeah, so there is...
Thank you.
This matter goes back pre-linguistic.
So, hey, we get to go back to the Neolithic era.
Yeah.
Well, first time this episode, but as is our want in general.
So we have these burials where rocks are placed on the bodies.
And there's a lot of debate as to exactly why, because it's pre-linked.
So we don't have like written sources explaining what's going on. Yeah
so
In general, if people have the general agreement that it's just somehow keep the person or the body down
Right, so
There's one interpretation that is that
They thought this person might come back
I think I'm like,
Rikulaka style, right?
Yeah.
To, off the commuted.
It's so they're weighing it down with rocks.
There's also the thought that they're trying to push them down into the underworld or keep
them down in the underworld, which is related to the other one.
But either way, that would indicate that this person is under a curse, right?
It's not a blessing to have them put the rocks on.
Right.
And we do, there are other examples too.
look at the testimony of Abraham and as Azul gets buried under rocks.
Does an absalom get buried under rocks?
Yes.
Job's family has the house fallen.
That is a general indicator that this is a death under some kind of curse.
That's part of what's going on in Job. It's not just that his family all dies.
It's that they die in this horrible way.
Right.
It's kind of unblast way.
Part of that with building collapses and that kind of thing,
Part of it is that you're not at-
actually buried also.
Yeah, right.
Right.
Like you're in this rubble, you're under these rocks,
and so you can't get to the body and bury it, right?
So there's sort of an abandonment thing connected to it.
A lot of times, when we're talking about the watchers
and his nasal and stuff, it's out in the wilderness, too.
But so yeah, these are all bad things.
This is a bad end, right?
That's answer me.
I know people love what I talk.
But yes, it's indicated that he met kind of a, he got his revenge, but he met kind of
a bad end in the process.
Yeah, cool question, Catherine.
All right, our final question now is from Clay.
Hey, fathers, this is Clay from Columbus, Georgia.
I was calling in to ask a question about the creature called A-Z's, Z-I-Z, which
seems to be a primordial creature similar to Leviathan and Behemoth in Jewish mythology
and mentioned a couple of times in the Psalms, but it doesn't seem to have that same chaos
implication. It's wondering if there was any similarity here to cherubs or if there's a reason
why you think that that one may not be portrayed as bad in mythology whereas the other two are.
any thoughts or comments be great. Thanks. Okay.
What I had to save this one for last.
What is the Z's?
Z-I-Z. I had to look this up, and I still only have the slightest touch of knowledge about
this now.
What is a Z's father?
Yeah.
So I've been told that Naital will help you get the Z.
Oh!
Wow.
That's an old ad.
Man, I haven't thought about that.
They get in the grace.
Yeah.
But this is also not ZZ top.
though the Z's did have legs and presumably did know how to use them, though primarily flu.
Yeah, and there is a wiki pedia article about Z's which defines it as a giant griffin-like bird in
Jewish mythology said to be large enough to be able to block out the sun with its wingspan.
Yes, which is a big bird. Yes. Now we're going to ruin Sesame Street for people.
is Big Bird AZ's right in let us know
So the place is in the Hebrew Bible where he shows up or saw him 50 and 80 or 49 and 79 he's mentioned.
And it gets lost in a lot of English translations.
And both of those are not really negative references.
There's one of the funniest things I've ever read in it.
at Jewish Haga da. I just thought that's close. One of the things I've ever read in a Jewish
Haga da. Sorry. Is actually about the Z's because one of the Haga da talking about the Z's
talks about how one time the Z's accidentally laid an egg while in flight. Okay. And the
egg fell and wiped out a bunch of
cities from the the embryonic fluid in the egg like the egg white I guess like
flooded it wiped out a bunch of cities and like leveled the cedar forest and
Lebanon right with the explosion when it landed and but this is the great part
is that after telling that story the Haga Daw says fortunately such things do
not often happened.
And that is just amazing, right?
I think we can all be glad that only happens once in a while.
Wow. It is not an everyday occurrence.
Um, but I, I, I, I, so I've seen the idea that it's sort of like the Jewish version of a phoenix.
Well, it's actually, it actually seems to be the Hebrew version of Anzu.
Anzu, I don't know what that is.
Yeah, we have mentioned Anzu once before on the podcast.
Okay, I didn't remember.
living in a tree. But Anzu is usually just depicted as a giant bird. It's sort of this magnificent
creature like of the gods. It's this primordial creature. It's descended from the sky and the earth.
So it's this creature and it's portrayed as sort of...
noble but also kind of mischievous because like it's supposed to make more so famous exploit is
stealing
The tablet that gave
Enlil like rule of the universe. Oh
When Enlil was the most high god he had this tablet that was like the deed the one ring
Well, it was really like the property deed the property like a cosmos. Yeah, I mean
But if it gives you a rule of the universe, no.
So it's given the right to the...
rule the universe basically. He the scroll with the seven seals in revelation by the way on that. But
that should be a future episode. So that he has this tablet that says he's the boss of everybody
and on zoo like flies by and grabs it and takes it to his nest like up on a mountain.
And so then Anne will says, hey, somebody help me out with this. And so
the earliest form of this, Nernerda, who...
As I think we've mentioned before on the podcast is linguistically identical to the Nimrod of the Bible
Who remembers described as a mighty hunter before the Lord right right?
Ninerna or Nimrod goes and
Managed is to in a feet of archery
Kill on zoom and get the tablet back
So he's sort of Ninerdas sort of has this hunter thing going on too
with that that's how to do
to kind of get promoted up the ranks.
But so that the Anzu was used by the Assyrians and the Babylonians as sort of a symbol of power.
Yeah, it's case.
I see that some depictions of it are of a lion-headed eagle.
Right.
So sometimes usually it's just a big bird but you can get some where it's got a lion head.
That's where you get the Griffin thing.
Yeah.
The Griffin connections.
So
So when, for example, I think it's in Psalm 50,
slash 49, that God says in the Hebrew,
this disease is mine.
Right.
It's, you know, I sort of reclaiming
this symbol of power from these foreign gods.
Like no, these magnificent creatures belong to me.
They aren't symbols of your power.
They're my power.
Right.
Uh
sort of in that reclaiming kind of context. So that's why we didn't talk about disease on the
monster episode because he's not really a monster. Yeah. Yeah. He's sort of in a different
category. A mythic being of sorts. Yeah. And through Anzu, people have tried to tie it to the
the Greek phoenix but I think it's closer to the Greek Griffin.
then to uh
than to the Phoenix, even though the Phoenix is also obviously a bird.
Right. Right. Nice.
Well, that is our SpeakPipe Paloza episode from A to Z's.
Thank you very much everyone for listening. If you can't get through to us live,
we'd still love to hear from you. You can email us at LordOfSpiritsAtAncientFate.com,
message us at our Facebook page or, like this episode, leave us a voicemail at SpeakPipe.com
slash Lord of Spirits.
And we will speak back down the same or another closely related pipe.
And join us for our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m.
Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific Zooming Soul.
And if you are on Facebook, like our page, join our discussion group, leave reviews and
ratings everywhere, but most importantly, please share this show with a friend whom you
know is going to love it.
that you know is going to hate it because like we said we have special prayers.
for those who hate us.
Or just ambivalent toward it.
And finally be sure to go to hfate.com,
stroke support, and help make sure we,
and lots of other hand,
of our podcasters stay up here.
Thank you, good night, and God bless.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits
with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung,
a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
and I be-
Be held, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts and
the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-12.